<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[A commentarye vpon the prophet Malaky. M.D.LIII]</title>
            <author>Gilby, Anthony, ca. 1510-1585.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1553</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72181</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11885.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S125398</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898255</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898255</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173568</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72181)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173568)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2065:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[A commentarye vpon the prophet Malaky. M.D.LIII]</title>
                  <author>Gilby, Anthony, ca. 1510-1585.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[176] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>John Day,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1553?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title and imprint from STC; copy catalogued lacks title page.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-L.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A commentary vpon the prophet Malachy.</note>
                  <note>Copy at reel 2065 lacks title page, leaves A8 and G8 and quires C, F, H, I and K.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Malachi --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:173568:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ To the faythfull brethren whych by worde and woorke are prompt and ready to declare them ſelues vnfayned folowers of the truth reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. Anthonye Gylbye wyſheth peace and ſtrength from the Lorde.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Did write of late a rude Comentarye vppon the godlye Prophet Micha (dearely beloued) wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyth many worldlings (as I am enfourmed) are very mutche gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued &amp; ſore offended, becauſe that Prophet dothe freate and chayffe the old ſores of their cankered co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences and holow harts: Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyally certeyne Charmers &amp; En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ters, whych would be named wiſemen and Aſtronomers, haue ſo farre vttered theyr malice, and ſpyt foorth theyr poyſon, that they are not content to rayle agaynſte me (whych were a right ſmal mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:173568:2"/> in mine owne cauſe and buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) but they dare lyfte vp theym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues (blinde buſſardes, not able to ſee theyr owne ſnares) againſt God his ſacrate maieſty, agaynſt hys gloryous truthe reuealed to hys ſayntes, againſt hys holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, foreſeing al thynges, gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng all thynges, yea reuealyng all thynges longe before they doe come to paſſe, alwayes to ſome of hys choſen, bothe the ſaluacion of the good, and the perdicion and deſtruccion of the wycked repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, the Charmers Chyldren as Eſay calleth them. Emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges thys nomber euen of the learned ſort, ſuch as the Diuel hath ſtyrred by the name of Goſpellers and the vayne tytle of learning, to ſhame the Goſpell and good learnynge (for there is no good learnyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy Lord god be thou ſure)
<pb facs="tcp:173568:2"/> ſuche I ſay as haue the ſhewe of knowledge and relygion, but fele not the power therof, hath bene ſo ſhame leſſe, that they durſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the falſe heade of deuylyſhe lyes to the infallible truth of god hys holy prophetes, the writyngs of theyr wiſerds, to the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the euerlyuyng and euer ſeynge God: Comparynge vyle chaffe vnto pure wheate, as Hie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>remi ſpeaketh. Hiere. xxiii. Theyr marlynes, theyr nolhardes, theyr walſh Dauids and Daruel Gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders (whome they wyth lyke fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heades dare pronounce to be by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, borne, brought foorth, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed and taughte, by the wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſpirit) the dyuel in playn eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe, dare they conferre and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to the chyldren of God, begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and borne a newe, neyther of fleſhe nor bloude nor any carnall
<pb facs="tcp:173568:3"/> or internall operation: But by a celeſtial heauenly &amp; diuyne byrth, regenerate and newe begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the good ſpirite of God. Whome we muſt needes confeſſe moſte able to ſearch and teache, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſecretes of mans harte, but the depth of God his great iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. Of theſe beware (deare brethren) the dayes are euyl.</p>
            <p>And no maruaile though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked deuil do roare, rage and raill, now eſpecially in this time, when his artes, maſkes, and ſubtile de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyſes, begynne by God hys holye woord to be vttered, diſcouered &amp; defaced. For he alway ſtriueth for hys kingdom of darknes againſt the chyldren of lyght, the true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes of God euer ſynce the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnynge, and hath euermore in his members chalenged a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge &amp; wyſdome aboue the wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="tcp:173568:3"/> of God, as appeared in the Sorcerers of Egipte reſyſtynge Moſes, in zedechia and ſuch lyke chyldren of the deuyll, reſyſtynge Michea and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true prophetes, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when thys olde ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in hys owne parſon te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Chriſt, caryeng him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> place to place, byddyng hym fal downe and worſhyp, and he would gyue hym al the kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the worlde and al theyr glorye. How be it the deuil in al theſe, doth beſtirre him in vayne, and fayleth of hys pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Yea, our Lorde and mygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God dothe alwayes at hys ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed tyme and good pleaſure, ſtoppe and ſtay this raging deuil, and cauſeth hys artes to faile his craftes to be vncouered, the wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of hys wyſerdes to appeare foolyſheneſſe, and maketh hys o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles falſe, hys aunſweres he
<pb facs="tcp:173568:4"/> vttereth to be moſt vayne and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuable, as we reade in the fall of Creſus and other heathen I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted with lyke mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And to our ſinguler comfort whych be Chriſtians, in the byrth of our ſauiour Chriſte, he compel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led al the idoles whych afore time by the deuils ſubtiltie dyd delude ſymple people to be dombe and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to giue any anſwer to their worſhyppers, and at the ſendyng forthe of Chriſtes Apoſtles, al the Charmers, Sorcerers and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ters, were made dombe and ſpeechleſſe. So ſtrongly dyd our lord by thys hys myghty captayn, bynde in chaynes, and keepe cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyue this armed Giant, and ſpoill hys houſe and temple. Now ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore howſoeuer the deuyll or the wycked world ſhall take it, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> burthen of the prophet Micha, I
<pb facs="tcp:173568:4"/> do brynge another burthen gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and heauye agaynſt al wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Charmers and Enchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and againſt al wedlock brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, fornicators and adulterers, againſt al periured &amp; vaine ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, agaynſt all extorcioners, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſours and brybers, finallye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt al that feare not the Lord, all and ſynguler wycked worlde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynges. I do brynge a burthen I ſay; from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce neyther learned nor vnlearned, neyther prieſt nor people ſhall plucke foorthe theyr neckes. The burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I do meane, of the waighty word of the great God brought down vnto men, by no blynde nolhardes, or wycked Marlines, but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> angel of god, by the meſſenger of the hye king, and Lorde of the whole earthe, whych vttereth the terryble tyme of Iuſtice &amp; vengeaunce agaynſt
<pb facs="tcp:173568:5"/> all the proude people and wycked doers. How be it vnto you (deare brethren) that do feare the Lord, I do brynge thys glad tydynges, that the ſunne of ryghteouſneſſe vnto you ſhal aryſe, and ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe vnder hys beames. Walk in hys lyght therfore whyles you haue lyghte, for for youre ſakes theſe euil daies ſhalbe ſhortened.</p>
            <p>And though the proude do rage and raill againſt my former trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, becauſe my rude ſimplicitie voyde of eloquence, my playne kynd of wrytyng, taſtyng of my plough gadde, lame in learnyng, long banyſhed from the ſcholes, farre from the Logician ſubtyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, Rethorycall aſſentacion, or courtelye flatterye, hath ſkraped tendre and daynetye eares wyth ſharpe bytynge treuthe, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to kycke, yet becauſe the
<pb facs="tcp:173568:5"/> poore ſymple ſoules, whych can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not attayne to the hyghe wrytyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of learned clarckes, hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed theym ſelues ſome thynge to haue learned thereby, bothe to fear God his ſacrate maieſty, and to walke more warely in their vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations and callynges: It hathe encouraged me agayne to offer my ſelfe a laughynge ſtocke to the wycked worldelynges, a ſpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge ſtocke to the ſpytefull Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſtes, and to a rable of ſuche, as ſhalbe pynched wyth the waygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye burthen and heauye yoke of God hys greate vengeaunce.</p>
            <p>The whyche moſte woorthelye ſhalbe layed vppon theyr neckes in the declaratyon of thys Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecye. Wherefore I beſeeche thee O heauenlye Father, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Spyrytes, ſo to lyghten
<pb facs="tcp:173568:6"/> my hart with thy holye ſpirit, that I maye haue the true vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge of the ſecrete myſteryes of the ſpirit hydde in thys Prophet. Graunte alſo ſuche larges of thy ſpirite that I maye to the profite of my poore brethren, dyſpoſe thys thy heauenlye treaſure and boldly and conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſet forthe thy truthe to the glory of thy moſt holy name. So be it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="biblical_commentary">
            <pb facs="tcp:173568:6"/>
            <head>The words of the mighty God by his holy Prophet.</head>
            <q>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He burthen of the woorde of God by the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Malaky.<note place="margin">The text,</note>
            </q>
            <p>This is the burthen &amp; wayghty embaſſage,<note place="margin">Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary.</note> from the euerliuynge Lord and almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye God, thys is the terryble threatning of God hys greate wrathe, againſt al the wicked of the world, both choſen Iewes and holi prieſthode, proud Pammie and wicked Miſcreant, thunderynge fourthe the fearce wrath of the terryble comyng of the Lorde of hoſtes vnto iudgement, written by the hand of the Prophet Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachy. The whych Malachy as the word ſoundeth and ſignifyeth an aungell, ſo the deuyne Sentenſes and miſteryes in theeſe fewe lyues conteined: hathe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſome writers to ſuppoſe, that the au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thor hereof was an aungel, and nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, and ſo is Malaky named <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> amongs the other Prophetes and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde an aungell in the firſte cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> the fourthe booke entiteled to Ezra the ſcribe: but we knowyng by the worde of
<pb facs="tcp:173568:7"/> god that the very aungelles, are myny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrynge ſpyrites, ſet to miniſter for theyr ſakes, which ſhalbe the heirers of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And that all Prophecye is enſpyred from god, poured downe by the ſprite of god into the hartes of his elect and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen ſede of Abraham, do value the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoryty of euerye one of God hys holye Prophetes, embaſſaders and meſſengers ſo hyghlye as an aungel coming downe frome heauen, yea thereis ſuche aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce and ſufficiency of heauenly doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne in the holye Prophetes, ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde and agreemente betwyxe Moyſes and the Prophetes, and betwixe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and the Apoſtles, that if an angell ſhould come from heauen to teache anye newe doctryne, ſtraunge from theyres taught heretofore? we ought to abhorre hym as accurſed. Wherefore we do take this oure Malaky, to be ſuche an aungel as is named in the ſeconde chapter. The lippes of the prieſt ſhal kepe knowledge, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd they ſhall requyre my lawe of hys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>outhe, for he is Malaky the aungell of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Lorde of hoſtes. Thoughe there bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> an hyghe Maieſtye in thys lyttle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>hete, ſpeakyng euery word of thys Prophecy in the parſone of the myghtye good, lyke an aungell callyng and crying ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e heauen, to brynge the chyldrene
<gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:173568:7"/> appeare wyth powre, lyke the goulde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmythes fyre, trying, pourginge and fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge the golde and ſiluer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the droſſe of your earthye mettayle, whyche is the chief matter of the two laſt Chapters. Thys is the ſomme then and ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of oure Prophet, firſt to warne hys owne people of theyr wyckednes. Than to rebuke the Prieſtes, which cauſed the people to ſinne, in that they traunſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the lawe, and cauſed other to do the lyke, by thys meanes to brynge al fleſhe vnto the feare of the Lorde, and to call them to repentaunce before the tyme of the terrible indingnacion of the myghty God ſhal brenne lyke a fyry fornace, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumyng and deuouryng the provide and diſobedient lyke ſtraw and ſtubble, both roote and braunche together, as is ſayde in the laſt chapter. Wherein we muſte marke diligentlye .ii. tymes deſcribed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penlye and euidentlye by oure Prophet. The firſt is a time of grace, wherin God chewſeth Iaacob, cheryſheth hym, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth hym by hys woorde, admonyſheth hym, calleth hym to repentaunce the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a tyme of ſeuere iuſtyce and ſtraight iudgment, the whyche tyme who is able to abyde? Or to beare the daye of hys wrath? The fyrſt tyme therfore wherein we are louonglye called by the worde of
<pb facs="tcp:173568:8"/> God, may not be negletted nor deſpyſed leaſt thys ſharpe ſentence be denounced againſt vs. <hi>Here, here, o ye diſpiſers</hi> &amp; <hi>peariſh.</hi> For a nother time ther is wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we be here warned, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fatherly mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie is departed, and fearce wrath againſt ſynne by the iuſt iudgment of God muſt be powred vpon the heades, and laid as a burthen moſte heauye and a yoke moſte greuous vpon the neckes and ſhoulders of the chyldren of wrathe and diſobedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. This felte Caine in his deſperate wanderinge. This felte Eſau after hee had ſolde his heritage, for he colde finde no grace after that tyme, thoughe wyth teares he dyd ſeeke it. Gene. xxvii. Hebr. xi. Iudas hadde an acceptable tyme of grace offered vnto him, whan he accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with Chriſt, when he dyd eate of Chriſtes owne dyſhe, at hys owne table, but deſpyſynge thys tyme, he betrayeth hys maſter, and therefore deſerueth to feale of the terryble tyme, euen in thys lyfe for an example to others. The wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked world lykewyſe, which wold not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the warnyng of Noah, promiſing mercye to the repentaunte ſynners, was worthely ouer whelmed and deſtroyed in the terrible tyme of God hys ſore veng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce, raynynge downe frome heauen vntyll that all fleſhe of man and beaſte
<pb facs="tcp:173568:8"/> was deſtroyed, ſaue only Noah and his family: which embraced the word of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation ſent vnto them, and regarded the tyme of mercy. This hathe bene the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caye, fall, and deſtruccion of all and ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler natyons and countryes. Fyrſte al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes warned by the ſpirite of God, of theyr wyckednes: and for their rebellyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt this ſpirite ſpeakyng in hys ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes &amp; Prophets: haue they brought vppon them ſelues worthye deſolatyon. For the wycked alwaies do accompt the Prophets ſeditious parſons, and diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the common wealth, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of god ſent vnto them, a burthen mooſte heauy and intollerable.</p>
            <p>And euen ſo repynynge agaynſt: God hys iuſtyce, vttered in thys worlde, they begynne an infernall and helly torment to their owne conſcyences, whiche ſhall in the worlde to come, gnawe and grate, boyle &amp; broyle, and blaſphemouſtly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> forthe agaynſt the iuſt iudgmente of the almightye God.</p>
            <p>Thys is the heauy burthen which ſhal be felte in that terryble tyme, whan the wrathe of the Lorde ſhall brenne lyke a brennynge chymnay, or an hote flaming fornace. When for the wayghte of thys greuous burthen, nothynge ſhalbe harde emonges the wycked, but wepyng wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge,
<pb facs="tcp:173568:9"/> and gnaſhinge of teethe. Thys is the porcyon of the wycked ſaith the lord of hooſtes.</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">The text.</note>I haue loued you ſayeth the Lord, and you haue aſked wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I haue loued you? Was not Eſau brother to Iacob, ſaith the Lord: And I do loue Iacob, and I doo hate Eſau. I haue made waſt his hylles and his heritage a wylde wildernes fordragons. If Edom ſhall ſaye we are wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, but we wyll retourne and buyld oure deſolate places, thus ſayeth the Lord of hoſtes. They ſhall buylde and I wyll deſtroy, and they ſhall be called the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked border and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people agaynſt whome God is angrye for euer. And your eyes ſhal ſee it, &amp; you ſhall ſaye: God bee magnifyed, extolled, and prayſed vppon the borders of Iſraell.</q>
            <pb facs="tcp:173568:9"/>
            <p>We do reade. Gene. xxv. That Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ac dyd praye vnto the Lorde for his wife Rebecca, becauſe ſhe was longe barren, and god gaue vnto her two chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe felt to ſtriue and wraſtle in her wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be, wherfore ſhe aſked councell of the Lord what this thinge might meane. And the Lorde anſwered two nations are in thy wombe, and two diuers people ſhalbe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate from thy bellye, and thone peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhal ouercome the other, and the grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter ſhall ſerue the leſſe. And when the tyme of her trauayle dyd come, Loo ſhe broughte for the two chyldren. The one was redde coloured, and all heyrye and roughe, and hys name was Eſau, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dyd come forth holding hys brother by the foote, and therefore was he called Iaacob. Eſau was an hunter, and a tyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but Iaacob was an heardman, and vpon a tyme when Iacob had made him potage, Eſau cometh from the fyelde all wearye and fortyered, and ſayeth to hys brother Iaacob, giue me ſome of this red potage, where vpon he hadde hys ſecond name Edom. But Iaacob knowyng by the appoynted wyll and pleaſure of the Lorde of all, thys neceſſitie to be laid vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Eſau, that he ſhuld thus become ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto hym, taketh thys occaſyon of extremyty to ſerue god hys worckynge,
<pb facs="tcp:173568:10"/> and demaundeth hys byrthe ryght, who geueth it hym wythout delaye. So that Iaacob nowe by righte, hathe recouered the enheritaunce, wherfore he did wra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in the wombe. And the Lorde God is hielye to be magnified, renoumed and prayſed, who hathe exaulted hys choſen Iaacob, and reiected thys rough Eſau, thys redde blouddy Edome, whiche dyd no more paſſe vppon hys byrthe ryght, then of a meſſe of pottage, thoughe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, whan it was to late, he did ſeke for it wyth teares and could not haue it, by the iuſt iudgmente of the almyghtye. Thus muche for the declaration of theſe two parſons and theyr names.</p>
            <p>Now muſt we behold the two kindes of people, which did ſpring of theſe two brethren, and had theyr names of theym euer after. Of the Edomites, and theyr encreaſe from Eſau their father, and howe manye Dukes and captaynes dyd come of hym, we may reade. Gen. xxxvi. Their begynnyng was from the mount <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Ioſue xxiiii. A roughe and cruell people. They dyd lyue, by the ſwearde as Iſaac theyr father dyd forſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecye. Gen. xxvii. Cruell againſt theyr brethren Numeri. xx.xxiiii. Agaynſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eſaiah xxxi. Ieremi. xlix. Ezechiel. xxv xxxv. And the hoole Prophecy of Abdiah
<pb facs="tcp:173568:10"/> is wrytten, onlye to vtter the wrathe of God agaynſt ſuch crueltye as dyd ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the father and chyldren, bothe Eſau and hys of ſprynge: wherefore the Lorde ſayeth: I haue ſworne by my ſelf, that Bozra the cheife cytye of Idumea ſhall be a wylderneſſe, a ſhame, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche, a deſert, and curſſe, and all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cities ſhalbe for euer deſolate and deſtroyed, and ſo ſhall Idumea bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, as Sodome and Gomorra wer. Iere. xlix. Agayn Shame ſhal come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the, for the malyce that thou vttereſt to thy brother Iaacob, yea for euermore ſhall thou pearyſhe and that becauſe of the tyme, when thou dyddeſt ſette thy ſelf agaynſt hym, and the lyke threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynges. Through the whole Prophecye of Abdiah. Of Iacob and hys poſteritye it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and of his .xii. ſonnes, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of came the .xii. trybes or kynreds. Gen. xxxv. And thorow oute the whole Byble we may learne, howe god cheuſeth cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, leadeth and tryeth this Iacob and his poſteritie, to make them an example of a ſpirituall Iaacob, and a peculyer people, whiche he then had determyned to chewſe vnto hym ſelfe, to worſhyppe and ſerue hym in ſpirite and truthe, to haue their heartes circumcyſed frome all fleſhelye luſtes, too make theym
<pb facs="tcp:173568:11"/> Iſraelites (that is to ſay) ouer commers of God, by faythe, conſtancy, pacience, and hope in God hys owne promyſes. Wyll you know then wherin God hath loued Iaacob? In manye things doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe. Firſt when he made hym in his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe, he dyd chewſe hym before hys brother Eſau. Gene. xxv. Roma. ix. God broughte hys brother by neceſſytye into ſubieccyon vnto hym. God cauſed hys father to bleſſe hym. God ledde hym into his iornay when he fled from his bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther. God dyd encreaſe hym and bleſſe hym euer more, whan Laban thoughte to bee gyle hym. God dyd delyuer hym from Laban, when he dyd purſue after hym. God dyd gyue hym the victorye, when the angell dyd wreſtle wyth hym, geuyng hym the name of Iſraell, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncyng that he had preuailed againſt God. God defended hym from the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyce of hys brother, and cauſed hym to fynde fauor in hys ſyghte. God encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Iaacob wyth. xii. ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, which reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the whole land of Canaan, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce he dyd dryue forth the enhabitauntes &amp; gaue it to theyr chyldren in poſſeſſyon. Namely the land of the Cananites, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thites, Amorites, Phereſits, Gebuſits, and Gyrgoſites.</p>
            <p>God did plage Egipt for Iaacob ſake
<pb facs="tcp:173568:11"/> He drowned Pharao and hys armye in the red ſee, god cauſed the ſeas to ſtande lyke walles, and made pathes for hys Iaacob.</p>
            <p>God cauſed the floudes of Iordan to ſtoppe, and ſtay their courſe, and to ryſe vp lyke mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taynes, to make paſſage for hys people the children of Iaacob. To paſſeouer howe god fed them .xl. yeares in wylderneſſe, that they neyther wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted garment to their body, neyther ſhoe to their foote, how he ſent them Manna from heauen, and ſpredde the ayre wyth quayles, when they deſyred chaunge of meate, how he did gyue them and drinke forth of the hard ſtone.</p>
            <p>God dyd gyue hym a law, to leade his lyfe, and to teache hym parfyte wiſdome aboue all nations. Yea the Lorde hys God neuer lefte hym, neyther dyd for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake hym, but alwayes went before him in a fyry pyller by the nyght ſeaſon, and in a cloude by the daye tyme. As for the battayles which the Lorde hath fough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten frome heauen for Iaacob and hys chyldren: they are wythout nombre.</p>
            <p>And the wonderfull actes whych fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyme to tyme God hath wrought for his choſen Iaacob, they can be contemed in no bookes nor wrightinges. God dyd ſpeake face to face vnto hym, he ſent for
<pb facs="tcp:173568:12"/> hym his Prophets and meſſengers, and at the length God ſent downe hys own ſonne to take fleſhe for hys ſake, of hys ſeede and linage.</p>
            <p>What coulde he do more for Iaacob that he hath not done? Reade the whole boke of Exodus. Deutero. Ioſue. Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and kinges, and a brief reherſall of God his greate worckes .ii. Ezra. ix. And eſpecially note the loue of God toward Iaacob. Exod. xix. where the Lorde ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing with thondre, fyre, and ſmoke, ſaieth vnto the houſe of Iacob: you ſhal be myne before al people, you ſhalbe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me a prieſtly kingdome, and an holye people. The whiche ſentence is alledged in the newe Teſtamente .i. Peter .ii. Of the ſpirituall Iaacob, ſayinge. You are the choſen kinred, the kingly prieſthode the holye people, a people wonne for thys purpoſe, that you ſhuld ſhew forth hys power, whyche hathe called you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thys maruelous lyght. Whych ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme wer not hys people, but now are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of God. Whiche once were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute hys mercye, but nowe haue you at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned mercye.</p>
            <p>Wherefore as it was then ſaid to the carnall Iaacob and outewarde Iſrael: I haue loued Iaacob, &amp; he aſketh wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I haue loued him, forgetful of my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites,
<pb facs="tcp:173568:12"/> euen ſo nowe vnder thys com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playnt of the carnall Iaacob, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God doothe charge vs and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempne our ingratitude, whiche wyl be accompted the ſpiritual Iſraell and the true Iacob, not after the letter and fleſh but in ſpirite and truthe. Where we doe knowe that the almyghtye maker of heauen and earthe ſo loueth vs, that hee is contente we ſhould be called his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, the ſonnes of the hyeſt. And is ſo carefull ouer vs that he that toucheth vs, toucheth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Aple of hys eye. And that he ſo hateth oure ennemyes, the bloudy Edomites, that he wyll deſtroye theym wyth euerlaſtynge deſtruccyon. Yea hee maketh the heauens aboue the holy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels in the heauens to miniſter vnto vs. He cauſeth the earthe beneathe, the ayre the ſeas to ſerue vs. And ouer all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures he gaue vs the lordſhippe and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, to beare hys image and to be as it were earthlye Goddes. And whyche ſurmounteth and farre paſſeth all the woorckes that euer were wroughte in heauen or in earthe.</p>
            <p>Thys mercyefull Lorde oure God (when we were not hys people but hys ennemyes, not ſeekynge after his mercy but goynge a ſtraye frome hym in oure
<pb facs="tcp:173568:13"/> fleſhly vanities) hath ſo loued vs that he hath not ſpared hys only begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonne, but moſt louingly hath geuen hym vnto deathe for vs, to delyuer vs from the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypte of ſynne, and the helly Pharao, to bleſſe vs, to ſanctifyt vs, to make vs hys children. To deliuer vs from cruel Eſaw and all Edomites. To bring vs into the country promiſed, ſalf from ſeas, flouds and waues of thys worlde. To feede vs wyth heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly Manna of hys own fleſh, to gyue vs drynke forth of hys own ſide, for Chriſt the ſonne of our god is the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny rocke, of whome all the faythfull. Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell doth drynke, and are ſatiſfied. Yet we not wythſtandinge thys greate loue and manyfolde mercyes, do lyue careles of God hys commaundementes, as thoughe there were no cauſe whye wee ſhoulde loue God or obey his pleaſure, whiche is thonlye tryall whether wee do loue him, or no, as Chriſt our ſauiour his dearly beloued ſonne teacheth. Iho. xiiii xv. Not much vnlyke to our firſt father Adam, who thoughte that God had not loued him, when he did forbidde him the tree in paradyſe, but deluded by the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll ſerpente, ſuppoſed that God hadde enuyed his furtheraunce in knowledge, and therefore beleued the deuyll to loue hym better, and to counſayle more for
<pb facs="tcp:173568:13"/> hys profytte then hys creator, maker Lorde and God.</p>
            <p>Lykewiſe are we all mooſte readye to runne whether oure luſtes leadeth and thys olde Serpent dothe hiſſe and why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle vs. But the word and wyll of God is vnto vs an heauye burthen, ſo that wee heare and take it not as a louinge leſſon taughte by a father or a frende, but as a greuous yocke and burthen layd vppon our backes by ſome tyraunt, or rather a frende. So that in oure deedes we cleare<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly deny that we do loue God, or that hee hath deſerued any loue or ſeruice at oure handes,</p>
            <p>Thus did the Iewes and carnal Iaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob our ſpectable and glaſſe to looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, thoughe their father was choſen in hys mothers wombe, and hys poſteritye with maruelous miracles foſtered, che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhed and ſet vppon highe aboue al na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyons, diſpyſe theyr louynge Lord, who of hys onlye free mercy had choſen them in Iaacob and refuſed Eſau wyth all his poſteritye, before that eyther of theeſe two children were borne into this world.</p>
            <p>And becauſe they dyſpyſed theyr God and woulde not confeſſe vnto hys glorye wherein he loued theym: Therefore are they worthelye reiecte, caſte awaye, and ſcattered a brode from the face of God,
<pb facs="tcp:173568:14"/> and dryuen from hys holye temple vnto this daye. The whych obſtynate ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, &amp; wycked vnthankfulneſſe of thys carnal Iaacob, together with their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy deſolacyon, ought to ſtirre our harde hearts and to moue our careleſſe mindes, to remember wherin our moſte mercyfull father vttereth hys loue ſo many wayes vnto vs. Eſpeciallye ſeyng by the fall of the ſame Iaacob, ſaluacion is come vnto vs (which ones were vnder the ſhaddowe of death before their bowes were broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we beyng wilde olyues, might be graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and be come partakers of the roote and the fatneſſe of the olyue kynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and natural. This report of the great loue of God towarde vs, whyche are the choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iaacob and ſpiritual Iſraell, how he hath refuſed hys own chyldren, natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallye borne of Iaacob, as concernynge the fleſh, and taken vs to him ſelf, which were hys open enemyes and ſtraungers from that people, as it is greatelye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, ſo it is alſo verie terryble. For therin alſo muſte we conſidre howe they dyd fall for their vnthanckefulneſſe, and myſbelief, that we be not proude, but tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and feare, and alwayes knoweledge the louynge kyndeneſſe of oure Lorde towarde vs. For if God haue not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the naturall braunches, beware leaſte
<pb facs="tcp:173568:14"/> it happen by any meanes that he do not ſpare thee, whyche art of nature a wylde Olyue, Loo therefore the loue of God, and hys goodnes towarde the, if thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde in goodnes myndful of the louinge kyndneſſe of the Lorde God: Or els con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywyſe ſhal thou be cutte of, and they grafted in agayne, whyche are the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral braunches, yf they do turne from their myſbeleue, and confeſſe howe greatelye god loueth theym.</p>
            <p>For we gentyles are thys ſame Eſaw and Edom here mencioned, yf we be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull, vnfaythfull and forgetfull of god hys benefytes, where as we huylde, the Lord wyl deſtroy, and we ſhal be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the wicked borders, and the people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt whom god is angrye for euer, as oure Prophet Malachy ſpeaketh. But if we only can be tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kful for al hys louing kyndeneſſe, and confeſſe and knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the benefytes receyued: than ſhall wee be the true Iſraell, circumſiſed in harte, the choſen Iaacob, the holye peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whyche were wonne and purchaſed to preache foorthe hys prayſe, whyche hathe called vs foorthe of darckenes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hys maruaylous lyghte.</p>
            <p>And oure eyes ſhall ſee the Edomites (that is to ſaye) all the vnfaythfull of what manner of Nacyon, Countrye, or
<pb facs="tcp:173568:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> kyndred ſo euer they be vtterlye deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Then ſhall we renowme, praiſe, laud, and magnifie the Lorde oure God in all our borders, becauſe he hathe ſo wonder fully ſhewed hys powre, hys myght, his iuſtice and iuſt iudgement vpon the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Edomites, the veſſels of his wrathe, and in contrary ſort, hath he ſhewed the ry hes of hys glory towardes vs the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayles of hys mercye, whom he hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared and appoynted vnto glory, whom he hath choſen before the worlde began, called in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende of the world, loued with loue vnſpeakeable, that hee woulde bee conuerſaunte and ſet hys tabernacle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monges vs. And bee oure god, and make vs hys people. To hym muſt we crye ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, holye, holy, iuſt are thy iudgementes O Lorde. To recompence the wycked theyr euyll wayes, and to kepe thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy choſen. To iudge the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Edomits after theyr own merits, and defende the ſimple Iaacob from all vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and to ſhew mercy abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to thy people, whome thou haſt choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Iſrael cyrcumcyſed in hartes by thy ſpirite to do ſeruyce &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to thy holy name, Amen.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:173568:43"/>
               <head>¶ Of Eleccion and Reprobacyon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere is a iuſte occaſion offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to entreate of reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and Election, in that the Lord ſayeth by hys pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, I haue loued Iaacob, and I do hate Eſau.</p>
               <p>And thoughe the matter ſeameth to manye learned men mooſte daungerous of all other to be entreated and taughte amonge the vnlearned, yet becauſe I haue my ſelfe thereby attayned to ſuche fealynge of the myghtye god hys mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelous woorkynge, to ſuche a feare of hys maieſtie, reiecting and refuſynge, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectyng and chewſyng whome it lyketh hym. Euen as the potter may make and breake withoute reſiſtaunce of the vyle claye, which he with his handes formeth and faſhyoneth as the Prophete ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. Therefore haue I thoughte it my dewty, not to enuy vnto anye, but to vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame vnto other my brethren, chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren of the ſame father, ſeruaunte of the ſame Lord, and pottes made of the ſame moulde, and mettall that I am and by the ſame onlye workemaſter. Nether do I thyncke the vnlearned ſo vnmeete to receyue heauenlye doctryne, as we doe
<pb facs="tcp:173568:44"/> make them. Onleſſe it be throughe their negligence, whyche wyll no more, dyly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently teach them, for lyke as they denie this doctrine to the vnlearned in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyne tonge, thoughe ſome ſuche hath as muche fealynge of the excellencye of the knowledge of God in Ieſu Chriſt, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Doctor that euer I dyd knowe, yet I ſaye as they do denye this and ſaye: that it is perylous for the vnlearned, ſo haue they within this fewe yeares, denyed the word of God, the teſtament of oure hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie father to the laye men vnlearned in the tounges.</p>
               <p>And yet wee all doe ſee, and knowe at thys daye (the Lorde oure God bee prayſed) that there be manye vnlearned in the tonges (eyther Latyne or Greeke, who hath attained to ſuch a deap know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God his wil &amp; pleaſure opened in his ſcriptures, that they maye be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared not with the meaneſt but wyth manye of the great learned ſorte. And (I pray you) had it bene well donne, that ſuche bees hadde benne prohybyted theeſe flowers of theſe comfortable paſtures? Becauſe that ſome poyſoned ſpythars, hadde ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered poyſon in the ſame. Nay Doute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe. For by the ſame reaſon, Chriſte
<pb facs="tcp:173568:44"/> ſhoulde not be preached at all, Becauſe he is a ſtomblynge ſtone vnto ſome and the ſauour of death vnto deathe.</p>
               <p>But Conſyder that it hurteth onlye the wycked and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it driueth towarde theyr Iornayes end, to the pytte of hell, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be learned in the Latyne tonge or no, for amonges both the learned and vnlearned, wee muſte knowe that there be both good and bad, holy and wycked, electe and reprobate, wherfore vnto ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought the truthe of God hys holye woorde to bee denyed.</p>
               <p>But that it maye be a teſtemonye towards condempnacion to the one, and the gladde tydynges of ſaluacyon to the comforte of conſcyences to thother: it oughte vnto al to be offered, opened, and publyſhed. Wherefore by the good will of GOD, we entende to ſpeake of thys greate matter, none other wayes, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in anye other ſorte, then the open-ſcriptures ſhall approue oure ſayinges. And wee doe ſaye wyth the holye Apoſtle Sayncte Paule as it is wrytten:</p>
               <p>Bleſſed be God the father of oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, whyche hathe bleſſed vs wyth all ſpyrytuall bleſſynges in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye thynges vnto Chriſte, lyke as hee hathe elected and choſen vs in hym
<pb facs="tcp:173568:45"/> him before the foundations of the world were layd, that we ſhoulde be holye and blameleſſe before hym by loue, who hath predeſtinate vs, that hee myghte freelye chewſe vs to bee hys chyldrene by Ieſu Chriſt. Epheſ. i. And thoughe there come ſome wycked men which were long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore apoynted to thys iudgement, whych do tourne the grace of oure god to laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiouſnes and wantonnes, as holye Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das ſayeth, yet knowe wee that wee are choſen by Ieſu Chriſt, that the glorye of hys grace, his fauoure and mercye to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs myght be praiſed. For we are the electe and choſen kyndred and hys people by purchaſe, that we ſhuld ſhewe the vertue of hym whyche hathe called vs forth of darcknes into thys maruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous lyghte.</p>
               <p>For thys Electe people onlye was Chriſte ſente into thys worlde. To theym onelye is the woorde of ſaluaty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſent, as Peter ſayeth to the electe by the for knowledge of God the father. i. Peter. i. Then to knowe what thys e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of God is, and what in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures it doothe ſygnyfye: We deſcribe and defyne Eleccyon to be the fre choiſe of the good wyll of the almyghtye God appoyntynge and preſcrybynge in the booke of lyfe before the begynnynge of
<pb facs="tcp:173568:45"/> the world, whome he wyll haue to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and accompted amonges the iuſte. Thys choyſe, this chewſynge, this afore appoynted purpoſe and ordynaunce of God, is a boundantlye ſet forthe in the fyrſte chapter to the Epheſians. That thys commeth of the fre wyl of god and hys only grace, freely wythout our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruynge, Contrarye to the vayne oppi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the ſcole men, the ſame chapter and the nexte chapter followyng dothe playnelye teſtyfe. Ephe. i.ii. And moſte euydentlye, the Lorde in hys Maieſtye, ſpeaking to hys ſeruaunte Moyſes. Exodi .xxxiii. declareth all thys to ſtand of hys mercy, ſayinge: I wyl haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye vpon whome it lyketh me, and I wil ſhewe mercye where it ſhall be my plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, for ſo is the meanynge of thoſe wordes, I wyl haue mercy vpon whom I wyll haue mercye. Paule alſo decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge thys place the worcke of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixte theeſe two chyldren Iaacob and Eſau. Romaynes .ix. Sayeth thus of thys free Election, when Rebecca was wyth chylde wyth one and the ſame fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Iſaac before the chyldrene were borne, when they hadde neyther done good nor badde, that the purpoſe of god whiche is by Election myghte ſtande, it was ſaide to her: not for the cauſe of
<pb facs="tcp:173568:46"/> woorkes, but by the grace of the caller, the elder ſhall ſerue the yonger. As it is wrytten ſayeth he: Iaacob I loued, but Eſaw I hated. Of the boke of lyfe, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſpeaketh. Exodus. xxxii. And Chriſte hym ſelfe Luke. x. Sayinge to hys Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles: Ioye you and be gladde, for youre names are wrytten in the booke of lyfe in the heauens. And in the, lxix. Pſalme, it is ſpoken agaynſt the wycked. Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be wrytten amonges the Iuſte, and put theym foorthe of the booke of lyfe. And agaynſt the falſe Prophet. Ezechy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell. xiii. He ſhall not be in the counſayle of my people, nor wrytten in the booke of the houſe of Iſraell.</p>
               <p>Nowe it is to bee noted and marked dylygentlye, that thys woorde eleccyon is taken after twoo ſortes in the ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſome tymes as it ſygnyfyeth abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutelye the free choyſe, wyl, and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, wythoute the reſpecte of the reuelacyon of the woorde and meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of ſaluacyon. And thus ſpeaketh the holye Apoſtle Sayncte Paule of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leccion, ſayinge of the carnall Iaacob: They were ennemyes concernynge the goſpell for your cauſe, but concernynge the eleccion, they are beloued for theyr parentes. For the gyftes of God, and hys callynge are ſuche, that he can not
<pb facs="tcp:173568:46"/> repente. Euen as you once were myſbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuers from god, but nowe haue attay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned mercye by theyr myſbelyefe, that they ſhoulde attayne mercye alſo.</p>
               <p>Thys eleccion expreſſeth abſolutelye the courſe of god hys woorkeyng, wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the reſpect of reuelacion of the word or anye of oure woorkes folowyng. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thys fyrſte kynde of eleccyon were thoſe hundreth and twentye thouſande, whyche god dyd chewſe and keepe vnto hym felfe in Nineue amonges the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters and the .vii. thouſande whyche god dyd leaue for hym ſelfe in Iſraell in the thyrde booke of the kynges the .xix. chapter. Yea, thoſe that yet are not, are thus electe, choſen, and amonges al na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacions both Iewes in thys long blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and banyſhement from theyr coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye, emonges the Turckes in theyr I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous wyckedneſſe, yea amonges y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Edomytes, the Sabees, the Indyanes, and Ethiopians.</p>
               <p>And in the late blyndeneſſe of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſhe churche, wherein wee together wyth oure fathers were all together I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatours, all Hypocrytes and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfayte Chriſtians, thys abſolute elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon whereby the mercyfull LORDE God dyd reſerue and keepe hys choſen
<pb facs="tcp:173568:47"/> vnto him in all places, all ages, al coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes without reſpecte of parſones dyd moſt euidentlye appeare. How be it this ſecreſy of eleccion muſt onlye be lefte to the Maieſtie of God, wher, whan, how and whome, he therby ſaueth and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth hys mercye. For to the blynde iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of manne, al theeſe people reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſuche lyke ſemeth reiecte, repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate and caſte awaye, as appeareth by Ionas condempnynge the Niniuites, by Elyas condempninge the Iſraelites and a long whyle, vntil God had by mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle from heauen delyuered hym from that erroure vnto the chief Apoſtle Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, iudgynge all the gentyles to bee a polluted people farre from the fauoure of God.</p>
               <p>The ſecond kynde of Eleccyon is ſet forth &amp; knowne euidente &amp; open by the ſpryte of God, worckyng in the hartes of the electe and choſen by faythe and truſt in God hys promyſes, teaching vs that we are the chyldren of God, choſen to hym ſelfe by Ieſu Chriſt from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynynge, and therfore preparynge vs to an holye and blameleſſe lyfe to the land and prayſe of the grace of god. The whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che eleccion beſides the daily experience of our conſciences may be approued by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teſtimonies of theſe ſcriptures compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:173568:47"/> together. Eſay. lix. Rom. viii. Ephe. i. Colloſſi. iii. and a verye brief and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit dyſcripcion of thys Eleccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ii. Theſſ. ii. in theſe wordes. We ought to thanke God that he hathe choſen you from the begynnynge by the ſantefyinge of the ſpryte and the belefe of the truthe to the whych he hath called you, by our goſpel to attayne the glorye of oure Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte, by thys gracyous eleccyon was Iacob dearely beloued in hys mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe, and Hieremy knowne vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to God before he was faſhyoned in hys mothers wombe. Hieremi. i. And to bee ſhort, al other the electe of god are thus choſen, ſantefied, and beloued from the begynnyng, from before the foundacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the worlde, from euerlaſtynge to euerlaſtyng. For there is no chaunge of tyme wyth God, ſeyng that all thynges are preſente in hys ſighte. For vnto him a thouſand yeres are but one daye, but the courſe and chaunge of tymes are in vs, oure dedes, oure knowledge in mans chaungeable wyſdome.</p>
               <p>Thys Eleccyon muſte of neceſſytye dryue downe the pryde, we haue of oure owne ſtrengthe, oure owne power, oure owne nature, or owne fre wyl, our owne merits, our own iuſtificacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of our own workes and bring vs to the fealynge of
<pb facs="tcp:173568:48"/> the myghty power of God, whych wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all in all thynges, to the reſtoringe of al thynges in our Chriſt, both in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earthe, by whome we are called into thys ſtate, longe before appoynted accordinge to his purpoſed pleaſure, by whoſe power all thynges be wroughte, that we maye boldly ſay with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, who dare laye anye thynge to the charge of the electe of God? It is God that iuſtifieth, who is he that canne con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dempne? who can ſeperate vs (whyche are thys choſen Iacob) frome the loue of God.</p>
               <p>Canne affliccion? can anguyſhe? can parfecucion? can hunger? can nacked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes? can peryll? can the ſwearde? For I amparſwaded ſayth he: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nether deathe nor life, nor angell, nor power, nor thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges preſente, neyther thynges to come, nether heighe nor depth, nether any cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature can ſeperate vs frome the loue of God in Chriſt Ieſu our Lorde, lo this is the loue wherwith the Lorde loueth his Iacob wherby we ſay: O heauenlye fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Lord of heauen and earth, it hathe pleaſed the that thou myghte ſhewe thy greate goodneſſe, mooſte liberallye and frely towardes vs, before that we were. And therefore before we hadde done ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:173568:48"/> good or yll, wythoute anye our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytes or deſeruyngs, only thorough thy free mercye to electe and chuſe, ordayne and appoynte vs heyres of euerlaſtynge life, and therby to make all thyngs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teynyng to oure ſaluacion ſo fyrme and ſure, that they canne not ſtagger nor wauer nor fayle, Where contrarywyſe if they dyd hange of oure worthyneſſe, we ſhoulde euer be doubtefull, becauſe euerye manne is a lyer, and all our righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe is lyke a ſpotted clothe, and nothynge but counterfeyte hyprocryſy, wayed in the balaunce of thy ſeuere iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. But the grace of thys thy fre elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon maketh vs mooſte certayne and ſure, ſeynge no creature is able to take oute of thy hande, O God. Wherefore wee doo lande and magnyfye thy name worlde wythoute ende.</p>
               <p>So be it.</p>
               <p>Nowe after thys doctryne of electy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and loue of God towarde Iaacob, the hayſynge and reprobatyon of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſawe muſte lykewyſe bee declared, and thoughe the aduerſaryes of thys doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne do ſeeme to denye, that there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch reprobacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the wycked, yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes are ſo playne, both here in thys
<pb facs="tcp:173568:49"/> prophet and Rom. ix. That nothing can be more euydent. For what can be more playnelye ſpoken for thys purpoſe, then that god ſhould ſaye before the chyldren were borne that he hated Eſaw. What was this hatred, but the reprobacion, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieccion and condempnacion by god hys owne mouth of thys wycked Eſaw, lyke as in the laſt verſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt pſalm, wher it is ſayd: that the Lorde knoweth the waies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſt (that is) he hath the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in hys boke in the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, he loueth them as is ſayd of Iaacob, he hath ſuche care ouer them, that they can not fal, but vnto the glorye of god, and theyr owne commoditie, &amp; by the courſe of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared together in that Pſalme: it ſhould be added, the Lord knoweth not the wycked, lyke as Chriſt ſayth: it ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be anſwered vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I know you not. The latter parte of the verſe is, that the way of the wycked ſhall peryſhe, ſo that it appeareth to be al one, not to be elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, accepted and knowen of god, and to peryſh, and to be as a reprobate conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. And Felinus forth of kymhi dothe note that that parte of the laſte verſe of the .ii. Pſalme. God beynge angrye, you ſhal peryſhe foorth of the way, dothe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde thys of the fyrſte pſalme, ſo that the election knowledge, loue and fauour
<pb facs="tcp:173568:49"/> of god and eternal ſaluacion cannot be ſeparate: Like as hys anger and hatred, reprobacion and condempnacion conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently do folow, in Cain, Eſaw, Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao, Iudas the Phariſeis, and like obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate perſones, ſo manifeſtly vttering the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to be of that ſorte whome god al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes hated: The chyldren not of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, but as Chriſt anſwereth vnto them of theyr father y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyl, who was a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer before the beginning of the world lyke as hys chyldren hath bene alſo euer ſyth the begynnynge of the worlde, and therfore muſt of neceſſity be hated of the moſt mercyfull Lorde, who is compelled by the order of hys woorkes, to vſe theſe wycked roddes and cruell ſcourges, for the chaſtyſement of hys chyldren, doyng manye tymes the woorke ſtraunge from hys nature, that he maye do hys woorke of marcye, peculyer vnto his nature. And than vtterly breake, hate, reiect and caſt away into euerlaſtyng fyre and vtter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, thys rodde and ſcourge, lyke a moſt marcyfull father, fauouryng hys chyldren and hating the rodde. Lyke as he ſayeth by hys Prophet: Woo vnto Aſſur the rodde of my fury and the ſtaffe of my indingnation, and after promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to breake the ſtaffe and caſte awaye the rodde. Pſa. x. Suffering in the meane
<pb facs="tcp:173568:50"/> ſeaſon yet theeſe inſtrumentes of hys wrathe prepared vnto deſtructyon, with greate pacyence for thys ende that hee maye vtter the ryches of hys glorye to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the veſſayles of glory, which he hathe prepared vnto glorye.</p>
               <p>Thus was Pharao y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> manifeſt ſcourge and rodde of God, to correcte, to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyſe, and to exercyſe the Iſraelites, and to ſpreade the power of God through al the world. Therefore was Moyſes ſente vnto hym wyth the rodde of God hys myghtye mercy, to breake in ſondre this rodde of chaſtiſemente. And the Lorde ſayed vnto Moyſes, I haue appoynted the to be the God of Pharao, and Aaron thy brother ſhall be thy Prophet, thou ſhall ſpeake vnto hym, all that I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde the. And hee ſhall ſpeake vnto Pharao, to let go the chyldren of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell for the of hys lande. But I wyl har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den hys hearte ſaythe the Lorde and I wyll multiplye my ſignes and wonders in Egypte and he ſhall not heare you. And I wyll laye my hand vppon Egipt and I wyll brynge myne army and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple forthe of the lande of Egypte, by mooſte greate iudgementes, and the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giptians ſhall know that I am the lord Exodus .vii.</p>
               <p>Agayne the Lord ſayth. Now ſhall I
<pb facs="tcp:173568:50"/> ſtretche my hande to ſtryke the, and thy people wyth a plage, and thou ſhalt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhe from the earthe, for therfore haue I cauſed the to ſtande (for ſo is the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue word) that I maye ſhewe in the my ſtrength and that my name maye be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed through al the earth. Exod. ix. Then the lorde ſendeth a greate hayle ſo that fealynge the hande of God the tenthe tyme, Pharao was compelled to crye the Lord is iuſt, and I and my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are ſynners as foloweth in the ſame chapter. Yet for all thys the Lord hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth hys hearte, that he purſueth the chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſrael to hys owne deſtrucci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Exodus. xiiii. So that reſyſtyng the power of god he periſheth in this world, and in the world to come he is appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the euerlaſtynge fyre prepared for the deuyll and hys aungelles by the iuſt iudgment of the almyghtye Lorde: who being refuſed and ſo openly reſiſted: iuſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly dothe geue ouer the wycked to theyr owne reprobate myndes wyth gready<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to fulfyll theyr fleſhlye deſyres, and obſtynat purpoſe to proſecute that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the Deuyll and the worlde wylleth them to do, and ſo cauſeth them to hepe vpon their own heades their own dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, treaſuryng &amp; ſtoring vp al their life long, workes deſeruynge the wrath
<pb facs="tcp:173568:51"/> of god agaynſt the day of hys wrath and vengeaunce, as the Apoſtle ſayth to the Romaynes.</p>
               <p>Thys reprobacion then is the declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of god hys ſeuere Iuſtyce, and iuſt iudgement agaynſt the ſerpent and hys ſeede, whom by the worde of hys eternal wyſdome, he hath accurſſed from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnyng and appoynted to euerlaſtyng torment. The whych woorke neceſſarye for the procedyng of god hys holy proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, eternal and neuer ceaſſynge regy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; gouerna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, becauſe it is the worke of the wyll of the myghtye god, whyche is the very law equitie and iuſtice it ſelfe, free from all affectyons, farre from all faulte, cryme or ſynne. It oughte to be knowen vnto vs al, that all fleſhe maye tremble and conſyder before whome it ſtandeth, euen before that greate Lorde and myghty god, who hath power bothe ouer the body and ſoule to caſt into hell fyre. To whom no man may ſaye: what doeſt thou? Being like the clay in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters hand, or the ſtaffe or axe in the hand of the ſmiter. Who offendeth againſt no lawe, becauſe hys godly wyl is the lawe it ſelfe, and to knowe his pleaſure, is to knowe the lawe, to follow his will, is to do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe, ſo that of neceſſitie this great Lorde is ſo farre and free from al ſinne,
<pb facs="tcp:173568:15"/> that nothing is good but that whiche is wrought by hym, nothyng can be euyll that he worcketh in hys creatures. No the fall of Lucifer the father of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate dothe vtter hys Maieſtye, dothe ſhewe hys Iuſtyce, whyche olde Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than and father Deuil, was woorthelye caſt downe into the bothome of hell and eternallye condempned to euerlaſtynge paine and tormente, becauſe he dyd ſo ambiciouſly and proudly clymbe vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue his appointed place in the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. And where the malyce of thys old ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pente cauſed Adam the firſte manne to mounte aboue hys eſtate, to deſyre to knowe good and euyll lyke a God, the maruelous mercye of God and ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable loue towardes mankynde cauſed and compelled this wycked woorcke of the Serpent to ſerue hys glorye and to tourne to oure greate commodytye and profytte, in that he rayſeth of the ſeede of man, a nother Adam, moſt innocent, and holye, agaynſt whome no deuil, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any helly power maye preuayle, by whome we are not onlye reconcyled vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God and do obteyne pardon for thys offence, but we are borne a newe, and as it were againe created into greater glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye by farre then we were at the firſt, for
<pb facs="tcp:173568:16"/> the firſt man had only a promeſſe to liue in the earthly gardine ſo long as he dyd not eate of the forbidden frute, we haue the promyſe of the heauenlye paradyſe, and euerlaſting pleaſures. He had earth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly meate and fruit, we haue the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Manna whych feedeth into life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. He was created to woorke in the gardyne workes natural, we are renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto workes ſupernatural, aboue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, heauenly, and celeſtiall. He was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer come by the ſerpent, we do ouercome and triumphe ouer the ſerpent, Synne, Deuyl, Death and Hell. He had the gift of reaſon and vnderſtandynge, we haue the rytche wyſedome of God hys holye ſpirite, wherby we dyſcerne our own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie and weakenes, and hys almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye power, mercye, and goodneſſe. To be ſhorte, where he dyd renne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, hyd hym, and ſewe figge leaues to couer his ſhame, folowynge hys fonde fantaſye. We do boldly beholde the courſe of god hys woorkyng in our nakednes, ſynne, and infyrmitie, and magnifie, renowme and prayſe our Lorde god whyche ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth hys grace, by our ſynne, whych vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth hys power by oure weakeneſſe, hys wyſdome by out foolyſhnes, whych ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth foorth hys electe veſſels, his choſen Abels, by Caynites the veſſayles of hys
<pb facs="tcp:173568:16"/> wrath. In wych Cain the fyrſt murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therar, &amp; therefore manifeſtly of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentes ſeede, appeareth euydentlye the iuſt iudgement of the almyghty god, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſſyng and condempnynge, in Satan and Cain, al ſynne and wyckednes. To vtter that he abhorreth ſynne, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it, beyng ſo farre contrary from hys nature, whych is Iuſtice it ſelfe, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from hys wyll whyche is equitie, and hys lawe which is iudgement. In Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao a chyld of the ſame father, reprobate indurate, and accurſſed, whom god ſtyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp for the declaracion of hys greate power and myghty arme, as well in the manifold myracles wrought for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whych nothyng had needed, neither had bene occaſyoned, if ther had not ben ſuche a tyraunt ſo indurate and ſo obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, to wythſtande God and hys Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes, as alſo by the ſubmercion and drownyng of hym and hys people in the read ſea, a ſygne and token fyrſte of the eternal and ineuitable deſtruccion and damnacion, whereunto the wycked are appoynted, then of the ſaluacion aſſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſealed vp for the elect and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, we do learne here by alſo the power of god whych the very Sorcerers, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemyes of god were compelled to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe before Pharao. Exod. viii. Wee do
<pb facs="tcp:173568:17"/> learne more ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſtice of god, whych iuſtice Pharao hym ſelfe was compelled agaynſt hym ſelfe, to denounce and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrme. Exo. ix. And fynally we may ſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed moſt manifeſtly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fatherly mercy of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god of Iaacob, whych dyd gyue the kynge and the whole people of Egypte a pryce for hys choſen Iaacob. Loo the loue towardes Iaacob, and the hatred towardes Eſaw. What ſhall we ſpeake of Iudas and other manyfeſtlye repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, whych are compelled by the teſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of theyr owne conſciences, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce them ſelues wycked, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to feare god hys ſeueare iuſtice and iuſt iudgemente. And to flye there frome by the terrour of theyr euyl conſciences, whych is more ſore then a thouſand wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, agaynſt ſuche as god doth leaue to theyr owne ſelues. The which terrible examples, the electe of god, hauyng be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theyr eyes, hathe greate cauſe to praiſe theyr heauenlye father, throughe hys ſonne Chriſte, who hath ſent theym hys hollye ſpirite of comforte, whyche wyl neuer ſuffer theym to be tempted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are able to ſuffer &amp; to beare.</p>
               <p>But where we haue two kynde of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that be aduerſaryes to thys doctryne of reprobacion. The one ſorte vtteryng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues moſt manyfeſtly reprobate, obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,
<pb facs="tcp:173568:17"/> and wylfully wycked: cryinge and blaſphemyng, we wyl follow our luſtes, what neede we to care howe we lyue, or what we do? yf we be elected w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iaacob, we ſhalbe ſaued, yf we be reiect &amp; curſſed wyth Eſaw, we ſhalbe dampned. Theſe Lucifers, not ſubmyttynge them ſelues to the gouernau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god, careles what becometh of them, muſt be bette downe wyth the conſyderacion of the maieſtye and myghty power of God, whych ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth not one ſparowe to fal vppon the earth wythout hys wyl and prouidence, neyther one heare to fal from the heade of hys electe and choſen, howe fearcelye ſo euer they ſhal rage againſt them.</p>
               <p>Wherefore (O you Serpentes ſeede) howe ſo euer you ſhall be offended wyth thys y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhall ſpeake, knowe thys: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as the myghtye God hath made the ſkatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſonnes, able inoughe to ſtay the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng ſeas: ſo ſhal your proude waues of your boylyng ſtomakes, and ouer buſye heades, be broken and brought full low, wher and whan it ſhal lyke the Lorde of al fleſh, by theſe hys weake veſſels. And lycence muſt you aſke, as dyd youre fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Deuyl, executynge hys tyrran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vpon the good man Iob, as we reade in the fyrſt chapter of that hiſtory, before you can lay handes, eyther of bodye or
<pb facs="tcp:173568:18"/> goodes of any of hys choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; therin ſhal you be lymitted and appoynted (as ther appeareth) how farre you ſhalbe able to extend your violence. For God holdeth youre hartes in hys hande, be you neuer ſo great tyrauntes, and can ſoone cauſe you to faynt and fayle from your fury, turnyng your hartes rounde aboute as hym lyketh beſt. And becauſe thus you blaſpheme God, bothe in woordes and deedes, followyng your father Lucifer, abuſynge Gods creatures, and deſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng hys benefytes, hys tollerance, and hys longe ſufferaunce, whyche myghte moue you to repentance (as holy Paule warneth) you treaſure vp for yourſelfe euen wrathe &amp; vengea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce agaynſt the day of vengea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. I do feare nothing at al to offend you with my wryting, neither do you pas any thyng at al what is written or ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though you vſe to ſwere, ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe, &amp; ſtare for a litle ſpace in a furious rage, when you heare &amp; feele thynges contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye to your poyſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But the ſcriptures of God, al good wrytinges, al truthe vnto ſuch dogges &amp; hogges ar vttered to this purpoſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may be a teſtimony of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the light of God his truthe reiected &amp; diſpiſed. Therfore for the elect of god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the courſe of God hys woorckinge in al his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb facs="tcp:173568:18"/> &amp; reuerence his maieſty, &amp; magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy &amp; renoume his holy name, is this writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yet doutles do I know amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt the chiefe veſſayles and choſen chyldren of God, ther be many, whych haue not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned to this poynt of doctrine of elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion &amp; reprobacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I am very lothe to offend, and therefore I deſyre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the loue of god to ſuffer me quietly with out theyr greefe, to vtter vnto other the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of mi co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which I haue here by vndoutedly receyued: like as I haue many times harkened vnto them, in the contrary. Fyrſt praying thus both of vs together vnto our heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>li father, know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledging our own infirmitie &amp; weakenes O father in the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, what ſo euer we are, what ſo euer we haue, what ſo euer we know, it is only by thy fre grace, for we wer by nature the children of wrath, &amp; we are not borne a newe of fleſh &amp; blud either of the ſeede of man, or of the wyll of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, fleſh &amp; bloud ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not reueale y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of thy heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly kyngdom vnto vs. But by thy bleſſed wyl, are we y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are, &amp; by the ſame knowe we that we know Therefore (O father) doe we commytte into thy handes onelye oure ſaluacyon. If oure knoweledge bee ſmall, yet wee doubte nothynge, but that wee are the chyldren of thy euerlaſtyng kingdome,
<pb facs="tcp:173568:19"/> and therfore by thy myghtye power, we ſhal growe whan it ſhal be thy pleaſure, to a more full and ryper knowledge of a more perfyte age, wherin our fayth ſhal be fullye able to comprehende and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the bredth, depth, light, and large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy great mercies, and gracious promyſes. But ſeyng thys power of ful knowledge, and parfite reuelacion, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth al powers naturall, and remayneth onely in thy power, and the lyght of thy ſpirite (O Lorde.) Doe thou what ſhall pleaſe the, to open to vs thy ſeruauntes and chyldren, depending of thy handes, ſo much of the light of thy countenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and at ſuch tymes as ſhall ſeme good to thy wyſedome, and fatherlye mercye. In the meane tyme thus reſtyng hollye vpon the, neyther can we deſpayre, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wil we be to much careful, although we can not attayne to the knowledge of many of thy woorkes, neither to the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng of many places of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but we wyl confeſſe vnto thee, the weakenes of our fayth, wayghtyng al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes for further reuelacion of thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous lyght, to be vttered vnto vs when thou ſhall thyncke of thy fatherly bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolence and goodnes, mete and conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, knowynge moſt ſurelye that thou wylt pyttye our chyldyſhe infanſye, and
<pb facs="tcp:173568:19"/> cauſe the ſame to ſerue for thy glorye &amp; our greate commoditye, ſeynge that we do erre, and are chyldyſh, as ſonnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch a father whyche cannot put of hys fatherlye pyttye, but rather as thou haſt bought vs vnto the, to be the heires of thy kyngdome by the bloude of thy naturall ſonne, ſo we be moſte ſure that thou wylt lyghten vs in the ende, wyth the ful fruition of the bryghte lyghte of thy countenaunce, that we may ſee the and know thee as this thy ſonne our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demer knoweth the, yea, ſee the our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther face to face, and knowe as wee be knowen. Thus reſt we only of thy hand to encreace our knowledge at thy good pleaſure, O myghtye Lorde and moſte mercyfull father. So be it.</p>
               <p>If you can thus ſubmitte your ſelues good brethren, to the wyſdome of God, woorkyng in vs weakelyngs what hym lyketh. Al the ſtomblyng ſtockes whych myght offend you, may eaſely be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Ther be twoo thynges eſpecyallye whych do ſeeme to ſtande agaynſte thys doctryne of eleccion and reprobacion, or of God his gouernaunce and prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, for al is one in effecte, the one toucheth God, the other man. The tyrſt and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalis, leſt that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked do make God the author of ſynne in the reprobate, the
<pb facs="tcp:173568:20"/> whyche doubte, we maye remoue fowre manner of wayes.</p>
               <p>Fyrſt, by the authoryty of ſcriptures. Secondlye, by the teſtimonye of theyr owne conſciences whiche be the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate. Thyrdlye, by the nature of ſynne. Fowrthly, by the maieſty of god whych is bounde to none of hys creatures, to make hym thys or that veſſayle. For the fyrſt Saynt Iames ſayth: Lette no man ſay when he is tempted, that he is tempted of God, for God, as he cannot be tempted wyth euyl, ſo neyther dothe he tempt any man. But euery manne is tempted, drawen awaye, and entyſed of hys owne luſt and concupiſcence. Then the luſt when it hath conceyued, bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth foorthe ſynne. Iames. i. And euen thus it appeared in the fyrſt fal of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde. Fyrſte, thoughe the Lorde oure God had warned and commaunded the contrary, our olde ennemye ſtyrreth the concupiſcence and luſte of the woman, wyth the goodnes, pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tnes &amp; beawty of the aple, then her luſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiuing this, bryngeth forth ſynne, entiſing alſo her houſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to the breaking of God his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. Gen. iii. But co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarywiſe ſaith Iames in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame place. Ia. i. Leſt you ſhuld erre &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eeyue any euil opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, euerye good gyfte and euerye
<pb facs="tcp:173568:20"/> parfyte gifte is from aboue, deſcending from the father of lyght, wyth whom is no varyablenes, neyther chaunge into darknes, that he ſhould geue now good thynges, nowe euyll, nowe lyght, nowe darknes. No, ſayth the Apoſtle Paule, let God be true, and al men lyars. Can God be vniuſt? How ſhall he then iudge the worlde? Rom. iii. Agayne, God ſaith by hys prophet Ezechyel: I wyl not the death of a ſynner, but I wyl rather that the ſynner conuerte, repente, and lyue. And vnto wycked Iheruſalem ſaith our ſauiour Chriſt: O Iheruſalem Iheruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, whyche ſleyeſt the Prophetes, and ſtoneſt them that are ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto the: How oft wold I haue gathered together thy chyldren, as the Hen gathereth her chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyns vnder her wynges, and thou wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not. Lo, thy houſe therfore is left de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolate. Math. xxiii. Loo, here appeareth the goodnes of the lyuyng Lord, ſo dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygently callyng the wycked to hym by hys woorde, by hys Prophetes, by hys meſſengers, and at the lengthe by hys owne ſonne, that he cannot in any caſe be accompted the authour of theyr euyl, nor cauſe of their fal. But contrary wiſe theyr owne wylful and wycked ſtobber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, is the cauſe of theyr euyll and the onely occaſion of theyr fal, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten:
<pb facs="tcp:173568:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173568:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173568:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173568:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173568:23"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173568:23"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173568:24"/> Thy perdicion and deſtruccion is of thyne owne ſelfe, but onlye of me is thy ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And infinite ſcryptures to the ſame purpoſe appertaynyng. That wee may ſay wyth Danyel: vnto the O lord, belongeth ryghtuouſnes, and to vs the ſhame &amp; coueryng of our faces. Dani. ix. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly. The teſtemony of the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the wicked, whych ſhal accuſe or excuſe them at the great day, whyche is alwayes of the force &amp; valure of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande wytneſſes, whych is the woorme that ſhal neuer dye but gnawe the wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for euer. Eſa. lxvi. Thys conſcience (I ſay) of theyres ſhall condempne the wicked, and what ſhal God then do? Or wherein is hys dreadfull maieſtye to be charged? Cain by hys owne conſcience, is compelled to confeſſe: greater is my wyckednes then can be remytted. Thou caſteſt me frome the face of the earthe (ſayth he) and I muſt hyde me from thy face. Lo, the iuſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God and hys worthy condempnacion, openly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed. Who dare then blame God. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in dare in no wyſe doe it. Neyther yet proud Pharao, who condempned in his own hart and conſcience, accuſeth him ſelfe and hys people, and iuſtifyeth god delyuerynge all men from thys wycked blaſphemye, ſayinge openlye: I haue
<pb facs="tcp:173568:24"/> ſynned nowe, the Lorde is iuſt, and I &amp; my people are wycked. Exodi. ix. What doth Iudas? Doth he not crye lykewiſe I haue ſinned, betraying thys innocent bloud. Math. xxvii. And to vtter in dede that thyng he felt wythin hys breaſt, he is compelled to take aduengeance, and execute a iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t moſt terrible againſt hym ſelfe, vtteryng to al the world hym ſelfe moſt wycked, and that the iuſtyce of God, punyſhyng ſuch wycked tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours and murtherers: ought moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelye to be feared, magnyfyed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerenced, throughout the whole world. Lyke as al the other wicked and deſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate parſones, whyche for anguyſhe of harte, and terrour of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, do mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them ſelues, doth euyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually wytneſſe vnto the worlds and, that ther is a iuſt Lord, the god of iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, whome they doe feare, and before whoſe face they dare not appeare, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe hym of anye ſynne, but rather ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng the cryme, blame, ſhame, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhment, vnto themſelues, who wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelye by theyr owne conſcyence, haue deſerued it, dothe thus tormente theym ſelues, and wyth vyolente handes, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge the ſynne they haue commytted in theyr owne ſynnefull ſoules and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes. Thus muſt God alwayes be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb facs="tcp:173568:25"/> iuſt, and ouercome whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is iudged, by the teſtimony of oure owne conſcience, whyche ſhall accuſe or excuſe vs at the great day. Roma. ii. Wherefore let no man be ſo foolyſhe, to ſaye, that God is the authour of euyll, vnleſſe he wyll bee accompted wourſſe then Cain, more proude then Pharao, more wicked then Iudas, or any other the reprobate from the begynnynge.</p>
               <p>Thyrdly, the nature of ſynne, beyng defyned by the authoritie of ſcriptures, to be a thought, woord, or deede, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye to the wyl of God. For ſuch thinges onely defyle the man, as Chriſt our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſaieth. Mathewe. xv. and therefore are onelye to be accompted ſynne. No ſuche thought can be attributed or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed vnto God, as can be agaynſt hys wyll, therefore no ſynne canne bee hys woorke. Neyther can he be the authour of euyll, whiche therefore is called god, becauſe he is the authour and geuer of all good, ſo contrarye to the nature of ſynne, and ſo farre frome euyll, that he tourneth all oure euyll to ſome good, oure ſynne to the vtteryng of his grace, oure lyes, to the declaracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his truth. No, thys is the parfyte woorke maiſter whyche woorketh al thynges wythout faulte or treſpaſſe, all other doe fayle,
<pb facs="tcp:173568:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> fault, and treſpaſſe, and ſinne in al their woorkes, that he may be iuſtifyed in all hys doinges, and al creatures fal down before hys face &amp; preſence. Who though he do woorke all in all thynges, yet doth he woorke the ſame to ſuche godly ende and purpoſe, knowen onely to hys ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtye, that thought wee be compelled to ſaye God is the authour of the fact, yet muſte we aunſwer: but not of the crime. Becauſe he is the mayſter of the houſe. and Lord ouer the family, and therefore maye doe anye thynge wythoute the blame of hys ſeruauntes.</p>
               <p>And lyke as that whyche is no faulte in the Mayſter of the houſe, is a greate faulte manye tymes in anye of hys ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes, becauſe it is breakyng of their Mayſters commaundemente. Euen ſo doubtles the ſelfe ſame woorke is ſynne in God hys ſeruauntes and creatures, whych to God is no ſynne, but an ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary woorke appoynted for ſome ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al purpoſe, eyther for the manyfeſtacion of hys power, as was the hardenyng of Pharao, or for the declaracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hys mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye, as was the fall of Dauid, of Peter, of Marye Mawdelen, and all other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunt ſynners. And wherefore (I praye you) maye not thys Lorde, thus vſe hys owne Seruauntes, wythoute
<pb facs="tcp:173568:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> any blame of ſynne, ſeinge that he hath created and made them all only to ſerue hys glorye, his iuſtice and his mercy. Or how can he be vniuſt, or the author of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye ſynne, by whome all the world muſt be iudged and brought to the balance of iuſtice and equity. Whan the firſt world ſhall be condempned for their ſinne and iniquitye, and we nowe lyuynge ſhall be iudged for oure ſynnes: eſpecyallye all thoſe which not onlye do euil the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, but are authours and fautours to wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked doers. Roma. i. Fourthly. The maie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſty of God can be ſubiecte to no ſynne, be cauſe it canne be vnder no lawe, And that onlye is worthelye called ſynne, whyche is done agaynſte a lawe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no worke that God doth, ought to be accompted euyll, eyther that he is the occaſion of any euyll, which onlye is the mynde, ſence, and ſpryte and power of the lawe, wythout whome no lawe of it ſelf is good. For euerye good lawe is the mynde, wyll and commaundements of God, and what ſo euer lawe is not the mynde, wyll, and commaundemente of God, as was the lawes of the Scribes and Pharyſeis, and of our late Papiſts, the ſame be wycked: who of neceſſitye were ſet vp the body of antechriſt to vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre their vnrighteouſnes, that Chriſt the
<pb facs="tcp:173568:26"/> ſonne of rightouſneſſe, the heade of his bodye, in his manyfolde mercies, more playnelye myghte appeare, and ſhyne with more glory. Againe to define ſinne to be the affeccion, mocion, or operacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any reaſonable creature, againſte the law of God: his maieſtie muſt nedes be ſecluded and excuſed, who is the law maker, the creator, no creature, hauing no euill mocion, nor led wyth any affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which might make his worke euil. Like as the creature is for the moſt part blame worthi, becauſe eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whan it doth the beſt of all. It is ſubiecte to ſome af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eyther ſelf loue, or hatred of ſome other, yea the Lorde God may vſe anye of hys creatures in any worke, without the blame of anye euyll, as well as the ſmithe may make his colles to flame, or to quenche them, eyther the ſame peace of yron, ſomtimes his hammer, ſomtime his tonges or ſtythye.</p>
               <p>Wherfore though very much myght be ſayd in this parte, that as the potter maye make of one peece of claye what hym lyketh, the ſmythe maye make of hys yro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuerſe inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, yet folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng the godlye wyſdome of. S. Paule, I thincke it more mete, to beate downe mans ſubteltyes, wyth the contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the maieſty of the myghty God,
<pb facs="tcp:173568:27"/> pronouncing boldly that ſuch as ſay (if my lyes and ſynne, ſetforth hys glory, why am I then iudged as a ſynner, let vs do euyll that good may come, and ſo in their wicked words dare make God the author of euill, hathe their worthye dampnacion al ready as Paule ſayeth. Roma. iii. For of neceſſitie which theyr eyes can not ſee, ſuch diuerſity of ſinne and grace, of rightouſnes and vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes, of the contraryete &amp; chaung of thinges, muſt be in thys wonderful cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of heauen and earthe, by the high Maieſtye of God appoynted and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, For what neaded the goodly crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of light? If ther had bene no dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or howe ſhulde this benefyte haue bene felte or perceyued? what matter or cauſe of vtterynge iuſtyce mighte haue bene founde? wythoute ſynne and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryghtouſnes? howe ſhoulde grace haue bene ſhewed yf no wrathe had bene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued? No, the mightye God thereby moſt euidently vttereth his maieſtye, in that he ſheweth how the heauens fal in to darknes without him, the earth into duſt, the angels into deuils, the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into ſynne, and ſo finally withoute hym all thinges to come to noughte, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he might be magnified creating all thynges, his ſonne our ſauiour renoumed who hath
<pb facs="tcp:173568:27"/> redemed vs al, his holye ſpirite exalted who hath renewed al vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be his electe and choſen. Now to what creature is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maieſty of god bound and found debter of his ſpryte. If he with hold it from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, hys dreadful maieſty may rightly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hold it, for who hath geuen him firſt to aſk any thing again of debt or duty? If his maieſty do giue his ſpirit, it is of his fre mercy and grace. If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth fal into duſt, if man fal into ſin y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al things may be knowne to be nothing without god: what blame deſerueth god or who dare accuſe him? No, let al fleſh fal down be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore his maieſty &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fes. Al things doth only reſt vpon the o Lord god, thou haſt created all thinges of nothinge, ſo that without the they all do fall to their ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, to ſhew them ſelues vayn and no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing worthy, weake, wretched &amp; miſera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, wherfore if we haue any good thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g it commeth of thy mercy, if we haue any weakenes ſinne or infirmitie, it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of our owne concupiſcence, luſtes and vanity, our perdition is of oure ſelues, our ſynne is of our ſelues, only of the is our ſaluation, thou made vs claye, pots and veſſails to thine vſe. Do thou with vs as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhal thinke good in thyne eyes, &amp; the ſhame ſhal fal vpon our own faces The ſecond cauſe which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerneth ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:173568:28"/> (wherby many miſtake this doctryn) is that God exhorteth man alwaies in his ſcryptures to good, and forbyddeth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell wyth manye terryble threatnings, whiche thinges ſemeth not to be nede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full (ſay they (ſeing the elect ſhalbe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and the reprobate condempned, by decree and ſentence geuen vppon them before they be borne. To this we do an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that theſe exhortacions and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninations, are very neceſſarye to bothe twain, becauſe God leadeth vs men al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, lyke reaſonable creatures, not lyke in ſenſible ſtockes or ſtones. And to the electe they are mooſte neceſſarye Pryckes and ſpurres, to ſtyrre the dull fleſh toward his deuty, as all good men fealeth and can beare wytneſſe. To the reprobate they are teſtymonies of the good wyl of the almighty God to them opened and vttered, but openly reſiſted, refuſed and reiected, accordinge to the ſaying of our ſauioure Chriſt. If I had not come and ſpoken to them, they had had no ſinne but now they haue no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe or excuſe for their ſinne, Perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture you wyl aunſwer me: they can not obey vnto it. What is the cauſe thereof I pray you? becauſe they lacke the ſpirite of Chriſte to leade them, you wyll ſaye. I dare eaſely grant you, but
<pb facs="tcp:173568:28"/> wyl they graunt thys? wyl they (thinke you) ſubmytte theym ſelfe vnder poore Chriſte, and the folyſhenes of the croſſe and not rather boaſte and bragge their wiſdom, theyr knowledge, and theyr vp ryght dealyng, and rightouſnes. Ar not theſe the men that dare thus boſte? We knowe aſwell as the Preacher can tell vs. Is the ſprite of God departed from vs to ſpeake wyth hym (as was ſaid to Micha .ii. of the kynges .xxii. chap. Or as the Phariſeis dyd aunſweare vnto Chriſte are we blinde? to whome our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uioure ſaythe agayne. If you wer blind you had no ſinne, but now you ſay you ſee, therefore your ſynne remayneth. Io. ix. Thus doubtles they are ſo farre from the ſubmiſſion and ſubieccyon to poore Chriſt, that contrarye wyſe they dooe willinglye and naturallye followe theyr father Lucifer, Who dyd lyft him ſelf arrogantly aboue Chriſt the ſonne of ryghteouſneſſe, and euermore fygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth agaynſte Chriſte, though the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye power and hyghe wyſdome of God turneth hys euell wyll and al theyres to hys glory and good purpoſes. None o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wayes then bodilye and naturall darknes whiche by the wonderful wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, clearelye ſetteth forthe the bright ſonne ſhine, and yet laboreth
<pb facs="tcp:173568:29"/> by continual courſe to ſhadow the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne &amp; to couer the whole earthe. Wherfore the Lord God to dryue a waye this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural darcknes from manne, exhorteth to iuſtice &amp; equitye, which is his nature and the image which man ought to cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfait. And alwaies co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges therunto agreable. And forbiddeth that he is not, that is to ſai iniquiti, and behorteth there from by his Prophetes and preachers publiſhing his wil &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure, which is the light and law moſt per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fit to man his noble creature, whome he hathe made for his honoure and glorye, whome he hath appoynted to beare hys Image vpon earth of iuſtice rightouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and innocency. But becauſe this i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage colde by no creature parfytlye be expreſſed, onles the ſame were fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſelfe ſame godhead, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe that all things beſydes forth had ſome inperfection, bewraying their ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall the darcknes as Iohn calleth it the <hi>Tohu</hi> and <hi>Bohu.</hi> as Moiſes dothe it name, The vayne vanitie, and wylde deformite, whence they were by creacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on altered, recouered, and brought into lyght and lyfe, as apeared in Adam fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from truthe to lyes ſtreyght at the beginning, now of neceſſity the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God (who only is good of nature, beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and taketh this office to beare
<pb facs="tcp:173568:29"/> the image of god inuiſible. Col. i. And to be the head of that ſpiritual perfection which was to be wrought in mankynd, by his a fore appointed purpoſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh the firſt begote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of al creatures, for bi him wer al things created both in heauen and earth, viſible and inuiſible maieſtye, Lordſhip, rule and powre, by whom and in whom al things are crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and he is before all creatures and in him al thinges haue their being. And he is the head of the bodye, he is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and firſt begotten of the dead, that in al things he might haue preeminence For it pleaſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father that in him ſhuld dwel al fulnes, and by him to reconcyle al things to him ſelf. And to ſet at peace by him through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud of his cros both things in heauen and thynges in earth, for eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſayth Paule which in times paſt were ſtraungers, becauſe your min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des were ſet in euel works, hath he now reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiled in the bodi of his fleſh through deathe, to make you holy and vnblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les &amp; without faulte in his ſight. Seing then that thys cannot be denyed to bee the courſe of god hys holy woorking to dryue awaye thys darkneſſe, &amp; to bryng ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to hys light to take away ſynne, &amp; to brynge man to a lyfe blameles the ſtate of innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy &amp; his own liknes: ſhal it not
<pb facs="tcp:173568:30"/> be moſt neſſeſſarye to haue preachers &amp; teachers to tel vs this ſame, and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhe vs wherunto we be called ſeynge of our ſelues and our owne reaſons no ſuche thyng can be perceiued. Therfore haue we preachinges and exhortacions as Paule ſayeth: for when the worlde through wiſdome knew not God in the the wyſedome of God, it pleaſed God through the foolyſhnes of preachynge to ſaue them that beleue .i. Corin. i. And as he alſo ſayth of hym ſelfe in another place: We doe preache thys rytches in Chriſt the hope of your glory, warnyng al men, &amp; teachyng al men in al wiſdom, to make al men parfyt in Chriſt Ieſu.</p>
               <p>Thus ſerueth then exhortacions, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortacions, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minations and publicaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the lawes and wyl of our Lorde God: that he may be knowen the Lord and gouernour ouer all the thynges he hath created, and the only law maker a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monges hys creatures publyſhyng vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to al that parfyt equitie &amp; iuſtice whiche ought in no caſe to be reſiſted. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto yf they cannot attayne, they muſt confeſſe and knowledge theyr owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrmytye and weakeneſſe, and ſubmyt theym ſelues vnder the myghtye hande of God, and ſo doynge they ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued as chyldren of the moſt louynge
<pb facs="tcp:173568:30"/> and moſt mercyfull Father, in ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of parfection as he hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the beawtefying of the bodye of hys ſonne our heade. So that the Lorde God dothe teache all, and lyghten all men that come into the world both cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and reprobate, wyth ſuch a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as doth the good Prynce, whyche vnto all hys ſubiectes proclaymeth hys ſtatutes, and publyſheth his lawes: but lyke a good &amp; tender father, he leadeth hys chyldren (regenerate and borne a newe, neyther of fleſhe nor bloude, nor the wyl of man) and guydeth them with hys fatherly ſpirite in the pathes of the ſame lawes, wrytynge in theyr hartes what is hys good wyll and pleaſure.</p>
               <p>In the whych courſe of God hys wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull woorke, the wycked hathe no cauſe to complayne, for as theyr father whom they do follow is named y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prince of thys worlde, ſo they haue the worlde at wyll, and are rytche royſters, and wealthye worldelynges, tramplynge vnder theyr feete poore Abell, and the deſpyſed Chriſtians: neyther wyll they change theyr eſtate wyth anye ſuche, no when they are called from darckeneſſe to be partakers of lyghte, of lyfe, and the heauenlye daynties, laid vp in poore Chriſte they deſpyſe that eſtate excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge
<pb facs="tcp:173568:31"/> theyr purchaſes, theyr marchaundyſe and theyr earthelye luſtes and delytes. Luke .xiiii. Vvherefore in the other worlde, they that here are oppreſſed, ſhall haue comforte and the other torment.</p>
               <p>Sutche is the order then of God hys woorke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge that by the contrayetie of the choſen and reprobate, of Iaacob and Eſaw, of Pharao and Iſraell, and the wyſedome of God, and the wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the worlde, he wyll ſet foorth hys ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtye, hys power, hys diuinitie, hys Godhead ſo mutche as maye be knowen vnto man (that is to ſaye) in hys wyſedome, Iuſtyce, mercye, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghtynes. For comparynge hys wyſedome to anye other wyſdome, nowe appeareth, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that it is very foolyſhnes, euen darkenes compared vnto lyght, deathe vnto lyfe, lyes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to truth, as Paule ſayth: Vvhen they accompted them ſelues wyſe, they were made verye fooles, and changed the truthe wyth lyes, the glorye of the immortall God, to mortall and corruptyble creatures. They folowynge theyr owne rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſnes coulde not come to the ryghtuouſnes of God in Ieſu Chriſte.</p>
               <p>Vvherefore of neceſſitye God dyd ſhytte all vnder ſynne that hys mercye myghte flowe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer al. And that hys myghty power myghte ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere, he hath created the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; earth, wherin we do ſe lyght &amp; darknes, death and lyfe, ſhame and glory, weakenes and ſtrength, lyes &amp; truth, ryghtuouſnes and vnryghtuouſnes to ſerue to the ſettyng foorth of hys glory, that man may be driuen to ſay wyth Paule: O the depth of the ritches of the wyſdome and knowledge of God. How inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehenſible are hys waies? How vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearcheable are hys iudgementes. For who hath knowen the mynde of the Lorde, or who hathe bene hys counſailour. Or who hath geuen hym ought afore hande? that he myghte be repayed.
<pb facs="tcp:173568:31"/> For by hym and through hym and in him, are all thynges, to him be prayſe for euer. Amen.</p>
               <p>And as thys holy Apoſtle Paul doth ſubmyt him ſelfe to the great depth of the wiſedome of God and hys wonderfull regyment and prouy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and wolde beate &amp; driue downe all fleſhe by the conſideracion of the ſame. So alſo al our fathers fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning hath laid this the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their faythe. Vvherfore Moyſes beginneth to ſtabliſh the faith of man at the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the creacion, and ſo forth by thorder of god his preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t gouernaunce about the thynges made &amp; created. And Dauid for a confeſſion of his faith pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth of this prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce Pſa. xcv I do know that thou art a great Lord &amp; a Lorde aboue al Gods. Althyngs what ſoeuer the lords pleſure was he hath made in the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s thearth, the ſeas, &amp; the bothomles waters. Agayn, by the worde of God al thynges were ſet in their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and by the ſpirite of hys mouthe all the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers that be in them. And Paule conſyderynge moſt deepely, and pronouncing moſt playnelye thys deuyne gouernaunce of the creatures, and godly prouidence of the creator, in all thynges for hys elect and choſen ſayth thus. Roma. viii. Vve know that all thynges woorke for the beſt vnto them that loue God, who alſo are called of purpoſe, for thoſe whyche he knewe before, he alſo predeſtinate that they ſhoulde be lyke fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyoned to the ſhape of hys ſonne. Moreouer, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath predeſtinate, thoſe hathe he called, and whome he called, them he alſo hathe iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whome he hathe iuſtified, thoſe alſo hathe he gloryfyed.</p>
               <p>So that thys appeareth to be no newe lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng or vayne doctryne of God hys prouidence and election. But the onelye grounde of faythe and certayntye of conſcience in al conflyctes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the world, the fleſh &amp; the dyuell, agaynſte Synne, Death, &amp; hell, as thapoſtle vſeth it in the
<pb facs="tcp:173568:32"/> latter ende of the ſame chapter and all rhe fathers from the begynninge hathe felt it. For how could Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by any other worke or creature, eyther by comfort of any other doctryne, ſtay hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience? but in that the Lorde God promyſed to prouyde for hym, and to ſaue hym from hys ennemye (who once had ouercome hym) by the bleſſed ſeede whych not by merytes, but by mercye and grace, and therfore of hys free purpoſe before ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted, ſhoulde be ſentte vnto hym to breake the heade of the ſerpent. Why? ſhould Abraham haue left hys country and hys owne fathers houſe yf he had not felt thys deuine prouidence, father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly care, free choyſe and eleccion of hym and hys ſeede? By the whych lyuely fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng of God hys careful prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and free choyſe, ſendyng him ſeede whan he was paſt hope of ſeede (concernyng his deade body and al the works of nature) and by the ſtedfaſtnes of faythe in the temptacions aboute the ſame ſeede to be made a ſlaine ſacrifice, and other gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uous temptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and aduerſities frome tyme to tyme layed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym, thys cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen veſſayle Abraham is called the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all faythfull. As by hys hiſtorye appereth a fatherly care of our god, for all hys people, bothe for bodyes and
<pb facs="tcp:173568:32"/> ſoules, for wyfe and chylde and all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. And Iſaac hys ſonne, that cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen ſeede, in whom al the nations of the earth were promyſed to be bleſſed longe before the chylde was borne, hath thys promyſſe of enherytaunce geuen hym by fauour, that the promes myght be ſure to al the ſeede as Paule ſayth. Ro. xiiii vnto whom and hys faithful ſeede this free promys and fatherlye eleccion and predeſtinacion (or what els you wyl cal it) was agayne reuealed and opened. Geneſ. xxvi. in theſe woordes: thorowe thy ſede ſhal al the nacions of the earth be bleſſed. And the liuely ſence and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng of thys eleccion and fatherly care of God, for hym, dyd then eſpeciallye ſhyne in hys hart when the Lord ſayde vnto hym: Go not into Egypte tarye here, I wyl be wyth the, and wyll bleſſe the, and thorow thy ſede ſhal al the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions of the earth be bleſſed. Gene. xxvi. And after that greuous temptacion vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doubtedlye wherein he was compelled for feare of the Philiſtines, to deny hys wyfe and call her ſyſter, and after the manyfolde contencyons wyth the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſtynes, wherein hys God dyd pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue hym, and at the ende in the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull myracle of hys chyldren, whoſe birthe right was altered by the vnſearch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>able
<pb facs="tcp:173568:33"/> prouydence of God the manyfeſt notes and tokens of the free Eleccyon and choyſe of God dyd apeare. And Ia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>acob choſen and beloued in his mothers wombe felte this fre worke of God his greate fauoure, who had choſen him be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore he was borne, and taking occaſion of the neceſſitye of hys brother, ſeketh the byrth ryght, the whyche God hadde vnto hym before appoynted and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed renouncing the cours of nature, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dothe he leaue and forſake hys fathers houſe and pacientlye taketh all trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles offred vnto hym, In the whych of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentymes vndoubtedlye hee fealeth the heauye and greuous temptations that hys fathers Abraham and Iſaac hadde before (for no creature more often ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth trouble than the verye electe of God) for the experimentes of his faith, whereby the lyuelye ſence and vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted tokens of hys fauourable eleccyon after manye battayles and vyctoryes myght be made certayne and ſure, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe preſent comforte alwayes mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred vnto hym eyther by ſecreate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration or manyfeſt reuelation, wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſynge the ſyngular care of hys hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye father ouer hym hys dearely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued and choſen chyld, as hys wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful viſion of the ladder and the angels
<pb facs="tcp:173568:33"/> deſſendynge from heauen doth declare, and the other viſion wherein the aungel dyd ſhewe him the partye colored ſhepe for hys porcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to multyply and encreaſe his ſubſtaunce, as alſo whan God byd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth him go into his owne contry from this diſceitfull Laban, and defendeth his Iacob from him, and finally the glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryous vyctory geuen vnto him ouer the aungel, comforting him againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare of his brother Eſau, dothe bryng forthe vnto his heart and conſcience the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſygnes and tokens of his heauenly father, firſt electinge and chuſyng, and after euermore gouernynge, guydynge and preſeruynge by the free mercye of hys dyuyne prouydence.</p>
               <p>Iheremy alſo choſen in his Mothers womb as appeareth in the fyrſt chapter of hys Prophecy, where it is ſayd from the mouthe of God (before I faſhyoned the in thy mothers wombe I dyd know the. And or euer thou waſt borne I dyd ſanctifye the, and ordeyned the too be a Prophet vnto thys people, then felt the moſte lyuelye ſygnes and tokens of hys eleccion, whan his fleſhe repyned, grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged &amp; feared to take in hand the executi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of thys great &amp; dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>baſſage, and the powre of God hys ſpryte doth
<pb facs="tcp:173568:34"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173568:34"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173568:35"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173568:35"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173568:36"/> touch his heart, and openeth his mouth to the pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting and rooting vp of al peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and kingdoms to breke, deſtroy and make waiſte, and raiſed him as a fenſed towne, a braſen wall an Iron pyller a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the kings, prieſtes and people of the lande. Nowe thoughe ſome tymes his fleſhe dothe grudge for the burthen of his office &amp; anguiſh of hart as though he had bene an abiecte or reprobate, yet alwayes after the brunte of temptacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vtteringe his weakeneſſe, he fyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the merciful prouidence of his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye father, to take a continuall care for him and not only comfort and aſſiſt him but alſo moſt euidently to punyſhe his ennemies.</p>
               <p>And to be ſhorte all the electe of God are thus choſen and called guyded and gouerned frome their mothers wombe, accordynge to the ſaying of the prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Prophete. Thou arte he that takeſt me from my mothers wombe, thou waſt my hope, yet whan I hanged vppon my mothers breſtes. I haue bene lefte vnto the euer ſence I was borne thou art my God euen from my mothers wombe. And then do they fele moſt ſenſybly and lyuelye this their election, when temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacions and aduerſities doth aſſayl and aſſaulte them, in the whyche conflyctes
<gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="16 pages">
                     <desc>〈16 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173568:36"/> brynge to an earthlye prynce, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare then with the prynce ouer al earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and heauenly thynges, the Lorde of al Lordes, the kyng of al kynges, what comly offerynges would be brought to hys deuyne maieſtie. Would any of our earthly Dukes be well pleaſed with the preſent of a lame dogge or blind horſſe? Nay doubtleſſe: they would thynke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues vtterly diſpyſed and ſhamefully diſhonored by hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhould offer them any ſuch. Yf nothyng then be accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble amonges worldlye men in worldlye gyftes, ſaue that only whych of it ſelfe is commendable: howe mutch more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord of hoſts, the Lord ouer al dukes &amp; kings muſt we be careful what we do brynge? leaſt he being diſpleaſed, do reiect vs together with our offeryng.</p>
               <q>Nowe go to, and pray before the face of God, that he maye haue marcye vpon vs. Thys is done by your handes, wyl he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue your faces, ſaith the Lord of hoſtes.</q>
               <p>Yea, heare what the Lord of hoſtes &amp; armyes, the greate &amp; terryble God, the mighty Lord ſaith vnto you by his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, you prieſtes come to the temple &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:173568:37"/> to the aultare to praye for the people, there you doe offer, you drenne incenſe, you make vowes as though you would moue me to haue mercye vpon you, and graunte your peticions, but thus care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you doe come bryngynge the ſame and blynde, pollutynge the breade of my table wyth your leuen of hipocriſy, makynge my table deſpiſed wyth your vyle offerynges, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I neyther can of my Iuſtyce, nor wyll of my mercy, receyue the faces of ſuche fayned hypocrytes, neyther anye ſutche ſkornefull gyftes. No, I youre God am a iuſte God, I doe not heare the wylfull ſynners. And to the wycked I haue ſayed: why doeſt thou take my name in thy mouth? I abhorre the prayſes, the ſacrifyces, and the offerynges of the ſynner. Fyrſt pourge thy ſelfe therefore, and then bryng a pure offeryng to myne aultar yf thou wylt haue me to receyue thy face. O gyue eare you prieſtes, you are negli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gent in youre offyces, and that cauſeth thys worde of God to be lyke an heauye burthen to you.</p>
               <p>Deceyue not youre ſelues and youre people, abydynge ſtyll blynde and hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge of bothe ſydes. Betwyxte God
<pb facs="tcp:173568:37"/> and the worlde, the Spyryte and the fleſh, the lyuyng Lorde and Baal, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther flatter your ſelues, thincking that God wyl receyue your fayre faces &amp; hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical geſtures voyd of true holines. No, be ſure you hypocrites, that yf the earthlye Dukes and Lordes wyll haue no lame horſes when you prole for your benefites, neyther wil the Lord of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth heare your prayers, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t your requeſts for your blynd and lame offerynges, your haltyng doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne, &amp; crooked lameneſſe in the courſe of your vayne lyfe and euyl condicions. But thus ſayeth the Lorde God to you preeſtes agayne.</p>
               <q>Who is there alſo amonges you, that wyll ſhutte the doores for noughte, or ſette lyght vpon myne aultare? I haue no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in you ſayeth the Lorde of hoaſtes, and I wyll allow none offerynge of your handes.</q>
               <p>Lo, what ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more playnly or more wayghtely agaynſt your couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes &amp; ambicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? O preſtes ſeing no man
<pb facs="tcp:173568:38"/> but the Lord of al men, the Lorde of all hoaſtes and armyes, bee they neuer ſo fearce, ſpeaketh theſe woordes: I haue no pleaſure in you nor youre gyftes, I wyll none of theym, becauſe you do not ſerue me, but your auarice &amp; your belly, for wer not that, you wold not ons ſhut the church doore, no nowe in theſe euyl dayes, many preſtes wyl not do ſo much as ſhut the doores of their churches, but gapynge ſtyl for gayne more and more, abide abroade in courtes and great me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s houſes, and though they haue great ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynges and mutche aduantage by their churches, yet wyll they not once looke in at the church doore, wher they ar na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the paſtors and ſhepeheardes, but lyke theeues come onelye thyther to robbe and to ſteale, wher thou oughteſt as thou haſt frely taken, ſo freely to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter. Thys ought to be thy ſpeciall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, namely to do good &amp; profyt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offence (though all other men muſte lykewyſe conſyder that the true &amp; good laborer is wel worthye his deue and iuſt reward) yea, and if thou wyll be a good ſhepeheard thou muſt not onelye ſeeke thyne owne gayne, but thou muſte bee prompte and reddy to ieoparde thy lyfe for thy ſheepe, els art thou an hyrelyng and a theefe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:173568:38"/>
               <p>Wherfore. O prieſtes, thys prophet and meſſenger of God tellethe you playne, that ſo longe as you neglecte your dew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties towarde Chriſtes flocke, and onlye ſeeke youre owne gayne and to ſaciate your couetous mynds the lord God will haue no pleaſure in you nor youre offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynges, be you Papyſtes, be you prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, exammyne your owne conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces wyth this queſtion of the Prophet.</p>
               <p>Who is there amonges you that wyll do any thing for nought? And feare the myghtye Lorde whyche thus chargeth you. And let ſome one be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d amonges you, which followeth no gayne but la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boreth for loue in the vyneyarde of the Lorde.</p>
               <q>For frome the eaſte to the weſt my name is greate amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and euery wher they brenne incenſe vnto my name, and a pure offerynge, for great is my name amongs the heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith the Lord of hoſts: and you polluted it in your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſaying: the table of the lord is polluted, and the word of the
<pb facs="tcp:173568:39"/> prieſte is that the meate therof is deſpiſed.</q>
               <p>This prophecy as al other the ſayings of the prophetes, are generall and agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth fyrſte to the tyme when it was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and ſo conſequently the truth ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of remaineth vnto all ages, the prieſtes in that time thought that in Iury only did remaine the true worſhip of God: but heare is aunſwered as in the tenthe chapter of the Actes vnto Peter, beyng of the ſame oppinion it was by reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion declared, that there is no regard of no place or parſon before God, whether it be Iewe or gentle, but in euerye naci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he that feareth God and worketh iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyce, he is acceptable vnto hym. Thys fear &amp; reuerence of god his ſacrate Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtye, is the ſweete incenſe &amp; pure offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge which the lord God requireth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the one ſyde of the worlde to the other. Therefore ſaithe the Apoſtle Paule of this general acceptacion of al nacions, glorye honoure and peace to euerye one that worketh good both to the Iew and alſo to the Gentil, ſo that in eueri place god accepteth the iuſt and heareth hym, but he abhorreth the ſinner with his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, which is the ſence and meanyng of our prophet, threatnyng to caſt away
<pb facs="tcp:173568:39"/> the prieſtes with their fained holynes, &amp; to receiue ſuch worſhippers which in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny place ſhulde worſhippe in ſprete and truth according to the ſaying of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt to the woman of Samaria Iho. iiii. Examples haue we ryght ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that the mercy of God, is much far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther delated and ſpreade a broade, then the holye wordlyngs, who only wyl be accompted holye alone ſuppoſeth. For vnto Ionas (not able to conſyder thys myſtery) it was by the mouthe of God ſayd and pronounced: Shal not I haue mercye of Niniue the greate cyty wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ther be mo then a hundreth and twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thouſande men whych do not knowe betwyxt the rightha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and the left ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d? Though to our wicked cities and vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunt contraryes, this exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple ought to be no comfort but a condempnacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as Chriſt our maſter warneth the phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. For if one poore Ionas could cauſe Niniue the great to repent and .v. hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth Prophets, apoſtles and preachers cannot pearſe our flyntyſh harts, what deſerue ſo ſtubborne people? The Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites dyd repente in aſhes and ſakcloth bothe Prynce and people, we gettte vs into Harneſſe and gather great horſſes to reſyſte God hys wrathe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:173568:40"/>
               <p>They weped for the preacher, we laugh at the preacher, They faſted we feaſte, They mourned, we play the hoiters like brainſyk beaſtes, yea in the kings court where ſhulde begynne repentaunce and in the contrye for theyr mournynge, we mutter, we murmur, we grudge, and we grone agaynſt God, againſt our heads, againſt our preachers againſt our guids The Niniuites dyd crye vnto the Lorde myghtelye (ſaythe Ionas) and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded euerye man to torne from hys euyll waye and from the vyolente oppreſſyon of hys brethren. We neyther cry nor cal but ſhewe oure ſelues vnwilling, weary and very lothe to come to comune pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to heare godlye preachings. Ah this compariſon to our cities is farre vnlike, and nothing but a manifeſt condemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of oure wycked worlde. Though amonges the moſte wycked, God hathe hys choſen chyldren as he had Loth, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monges the Sodomites. For the Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites hadde a greate noumber bothe of their heades and inferioure people fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge the Lorde of heauen and earthe, and therefore was Ionas readilye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued. Wee haue not one niſte (as the Pſalme ſayeth) no not one, God loketh downe from heauen and ſeeth vs al vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profytable,
<pb facs="tcp:173568:40"/> all declining from the way, all workynge wickednes, neyther prieſt nor writer working the worthy workes of repentaunce. To conclude all in two wordes. They dyd ceaſe from ſynne, we do all encreaſe oure ſynne, whyche is oure condempnacion, yet in oure awne countrye we nothinge doubt, but God hathe hys choſen and knoweth theym, and cauſeth them to confeſſe hys holye name, to call their brethren too repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and to glorify the myghty pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God. In manye other countryes we haue examples alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes had hys people, whyche dyd offre vnto hym acceptable ſacrifice emonges the heythen, as in Siria Naman, the quene of the Southe, Hyra the kyng of Tyrus. In Madian Iethro, the father in lawe of Moiſes, the wydowe of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rephta, &amp; in dyuerſe other regions, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as they were all made for the glorye of God, ſo was there alwaye ſumme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monges them, that by marking his wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous woorckes in the creation of the worlde and gouernaunce of the ſame, or elſe by ſecrete inſpiracion, where there lacked open teachyng, did magnyfy his name and offre the calues of theyr lips, that is to ſaye: contynuall prayſes and
<pb facs="tcp:173568:41"/> rehearſynge of his maruelous workes, wyth due obedience vnto the generall rules of his commaundementes, which he alway preferreth to al ſacrifices, and counteth it moſte pure incenſe, and an offerynge moſte pleaſaunt. Wherefore the Iewes warrefarre deceyued, which thoughte them ſelues onlye the people of God, becauſe they had the circumſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion &amp; the ſacrifices, lykewyſe we Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians maye not boaſte of oure name, of our profeſſion, of our baptime deſpiſing all other people, and lyuinge contrarye to the wyll of God, vttered by Chriſte, contrarye to oure profeſſyon promyſed in baptyſme, for as the Lorde God had manye of hys people at thys tyme of oure prophet ſcattered from the Eaſt to the Weſt, thoughe neuer in fleſh cyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcyſed, and as oure ſauyour Chriſte ſaith to the Iewes bragyng of theyr fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Abraham, that god hys father was able to rayſe vp ſtones to be ſonnes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Abraham, ſo may it be ſayde vnto vs counterfayte Chriſtians, whyche wyth our Laſciuious lyfe do pollute our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. For we muſte knowe that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſion neither vncircu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſicion, neither waſhing nor not waſhing of the fleſhe is anye thyng, but a new creature renewed with God hys holy ſpirit is all
<pb facs="tcp:173568:41"/> together, which in all places is ready to offer a pure offerynge of thanckes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, miniſtryng iuſtyce, and working mercye. In the time of Malachy the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Lord was deſpyſed by the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſnes of the prieſts, hys name was polluted by theyr Laſciuious lyfe, the prieſts ſayd: the meate of the Lords ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is not to be regarded, it is no lyuing but beggary to ſerue the Lorde, we wyl not labour therfore in the Lords houſe, we wyll not ſhutte the dore for nought, neyther lyght a candle vpon hys table wythout ſome rewarde.</p>
               <p>Euen as our prieſtes at this day (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthely concernyng theyr offyce, but worthely concerning the wycked ſpoils of their liuings) do lament that the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itie wyll bryng them to extreme penury and beggarye. And ſome not worthy of v.li. lyuinge, from the churche, can ſaye what is, xl. pound, what is an hundreth pounde, and ſome Lordlye Byſhoppes can ſaye what is D. marke. Now wher the laye men do wyckedly in takyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thynge from you: Doubtleſſe you do muche the worſſe in cauſinge the worde of God to be deſpyſed through your co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſe deſyres. Whereby you dooe make the Table of the Lorde deſpyſed,
<pb facs="tcp:173568:42"/> and make all men vnwillynge to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre meate to youre ſacryfices that is to ſaye to ayde and to releaue you to the encreaſe of your lyuynges.</p>
               <p>I do paſſe ouer becauſe I wold haue it buryed in ſilence, how the table of the Lord was polluted of late in our popiſh time, both with the blindnes of the thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges offered there vppon, and the dombe Popiſhe ceremonyes heaped as it were wode heapes, the worde wyll and orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of God vtterly deſpiſed, and ſo many as God hathe opened theyr eyes, doth behold it and lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Yet you pope holye Papiſtes ſaye.</p>
               <q>Loo oure greate payne and wearynes do we brynge.</q>
               <p>As the Phariſey ſaye in the Goſpell magnifying hym ſelfe and his workes, loo I do faſt twyſe in the weake, and I geue the tythes of all that I haue, &amp; our Phariſes and poope holye prelates ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling theyr lyppe labours, theyr prayers, and faſtings, and ſuch other holines to other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, beleuing their lyes following the preceptes and doctrine of men, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hath an outward ſhew of wyſdome by ſuperſticion and humblinge of theyr ſelues do bring laborious and paynful workes as they thincke.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:173568:42"/>
               <q>But the Lorde of hoſtes ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, you myght blowe it away.</q>
               <p>Suche are the workes you do boaſte, ſo weake and vnweyldye, that they are not of ſo muche force and ſtrengthe as one blaſte of wynde, no not youre God your Idol your popiſh wafer cake, was able in all hys powre to wythſtande one blaſt of winde, and how much leſſe then was all your wyl holines and other po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh chaffer. Yea the whole kingdome of Antechriſte ſhall be blowne a waye and theyr kyng deſtroyed with the breath of God hys mouthe. And the blaſte of hys ſpirite.</p>
               <q>And you haue brought the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine the ſicke, the lame, &amp; bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge ſuche an offerynge, ſhal I receiue it of your hand fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably, ſayth the Lorde? No cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is the deceitful, which hath the male in his flocke, and doth vowe and offre corrupcion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lorde, for I am a greate kyng ſayth the Lord of hoſtes: and my name is terrible amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the heythen.</q>
               <pb facs="tcp:173568:43"/>
               <p>The Lorde wyll haue nothynge gotten by rauyne, by robberye, by ſpoyl and by bryberye, no he alloweth no ſuche ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce, no ſuche offerynge as is gotten of the ſpoile of our brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This is not his honour, no it were much his diſhonoure to admitte ſuch ſeruauntes. This were as pleaſaunt a thynge to hym, as it is to a naturall father to robbe or to ſleye the naturall chyld in the eies of hys fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to brynge to hys father parte of the ſpoyl for a preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Thinkeſt thou the carnall father wyl receiue this tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully? nay doubtleſſe. No more wyl the heauenly father receyue any offerynge, ſacrifice, praiers or almes fauourably, which ſuch Prieſtes and Byſhops brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, as takinge greate lyuinges, forth of poore mens laboures, doth no part of there dutye, whiche is playne theft and robbery. But as the Iuſte Lord hateth all diſceite in all menne, and that which commeth vnder the cloke of holynes eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, &amp; as the blynde, lame, and mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med beaſt, is an vnſeamelye ſacryfyce to be broughte to the myghtye God, as all ſuche ſacryfycers wyth theyr pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentes, ſacrifices and offerynges are to be dyſpiſed amonges the people. So muche more the prieſt, who ſhoulde ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare</p>
               <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
